<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Unum necessarium, or, The great duty of a Christian in two tracts : the one, Of adhering to God, written in Latin, by Albertus Magnus, the other, Of the love of God, written in high- Dutch, by John Staupitz / both faithfully translated into English for the promoting of primitive Christianity.</title>
            <title>De adhaerendo Deo. English. 1692</title>
            <author>Albertus, Magnus, Saint, 1193?-1280.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1692</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 193 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 93 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A76021</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A878</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R42992</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">38876078</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 38876078</idno>
            <idno type="VID">152164</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A76021)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 152164)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2281:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Unum necessarium, or, The great duty of a Christian in two tracts : the one, Of adhering to God, written in Latin, by Albertus Magnus, the other, Of the love of God, written in high- Dutch, by John Staupitz / both faithfully translated into English for the promoting of primitive Christianity.</title>
                  <title>De adhaerendo Deo. English. 1692</title>
                  <author>Albertus, Magnus, Saint, 1193?-1280.</author>
                  <author>Johannes von Kastl, 15th cent.</author>
                  <author>Staupitz, Johann von, d. 1524.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 70, [2], 71-   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Ric. Baldwin ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1692.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>De adhaerendo Deo has also been attributed to Johannes von Kastl.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained and tightly bound, with loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Second part has continuous paging and special t.p.: Two ancient spiritual treatises of Dr. John Staupitz, Abbot of St. Peters at Saltsburg in Germany, concerning the sweet love of God, and our holy Christian faith.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: William Andrews Clark Memorial Library, University of California, Los Angeles.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Catholic authors.</term>
               <term>God --  Worship and love.</term>
               <term>Faith --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:152164:1"/>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>num Neceſſarium, OR THE Great Duty OF A CHRISTIAN, In Two TRACTS; The one <hi>Of Adhering to God:</hi> Written in Latin, by <hi>Albertus Magnus:</hi> The other <hi>Of the Love of God:</hi> Written in High-Dutch, by <hi>John Staupitz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Both Faithfully Tranſlated into</hi> Engliſh <hi>for the Promoting of</hi> Primitive Chriſtianity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Ric. Baldwin,</hi> near the <hi>Oxford-Arms</hi> in <hi>Warwick-Lane.</hi> 1692</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:152164:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152164:2"/>
            <head>A PREFACE To the following Little Book of <hi>Albertus Magnus.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>HAving found by experience, how diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult it is to procure either more effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual Laws, or an effectual Executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thoſe we have already for an External Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, or reſtraint of ſuch ſcandalous ſins, as are no leſs ſhameful, than pernicious to a Chriſtian State, and yet are daily every where committed with great Preſumption and Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, in Contempt of Religion, and Affront to the Laws and Government of this Nation; and that this difficulty proceeds not ſo much from the prevalence of Impiety and Impudence of the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders, tho very great, as from want of Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuine Piety, through corruption of the Notions of the Ancient Principles thereof, by the ſpecious Deceits of the Wiſdom of the World, in ſuch as make Profeſſion of Religion, and whoſe advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges for promoting ſo good and neceſſary a work are no leſs than their Obligations: I obſerved
<pb facs="tcp:152164:3"/>that the Internal Reformation of the decays and this corruption of Genuine Piety in the Soul in ſuch as pretend to Religion, and have received ſome principles of it, is not only a more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent work but abſolutely neceſſary to effect that External Reformation, which how needful ſoever, is never like to be vigorouſly and conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly promoted, ſo long as this is neglected. And therefore leaving that to the care and induſtry of ſuch as have better advantage to promote it, I thought it more proper for my Circumſtances to apply my thoughts to this Reſtauration of the Ancient Genuine Chriſtianity.</p>
            <p>I had long ſince taken notice of other <hi>Cauſes of the Decay of Chriſtian Piety</hi> among Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, than thoſe mentioned in a late Book of that Title, and for Reſtoration of the Ancient Genuine Chriſtian Piety, as one proper mean, had thoughts of tranſlating ſome Tracts of ſome of the Ancient Chriſtians, and lately diſcourſing with a perſon of good Learning, and equal piety, who being well skilled, not only in thê Learned Languages, but alſo in divers Modern, was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to tranſlate <hi>John Staupitz of the Love of God,</hi> out of High-Dutch, I perſwaded him alſo to Tranſlate out of Latin, and prefix to that, this which I lately met with, of <hi>Albertus Magnus, De adhaerendo Deo,</hi> who tho not ſo Ancient as ſome intended (for he lived but
<pb facs="tcp:152164:3"/>between four and five hundred years ſince) yet hath treated and inculcated a Subject very proper for my purpoſe, and ſo needful to the ſickly state of our times, that to ſome, who are no mean Proficients in the Religion of this Age, I doubt it may ſeem almoſt impracticable at firſt. And therefore to prevent ſuch miſtakes to the preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice of themſelves and others, I ſhall offer theſe Obſervations to their better conſideration.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>I.</hi> The <hi>Subject</hi> is no other than the Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Principle of all piety, the great and indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſable Command, <hi>Mat. 22.36. Mar 12.30.</hi> The Removal of the Impediments (which is not only recommended, <hi>Mat. 5.29, 30.18.8, 9.</hi> and <hi>6.19, 34.</hi> and <hi>1 Cor. 7.29, 30, 31.</hi> but aſſerted to be indiſpenſably neceſſary, <hi>Mat. 6.24. 1 Joh. 2.15.</hi> even to the State of Chriſtianity, <hi>Luk. 14.26, 27, 33.</hi> and the practice or continual Attendance to the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of the moſt direct and immediate Acts of it, <hi>1 Theſ. 5.17. Col. 4.2. Luk. 18.1.</hi> and <hi>12.36, 37.</hi> The manner with the chief powers of the Soul, <hi>Joh. 4.24.</hi> the End, to partake of the Divine Nature, <hi>2 Pet. 1.4.</hi> be changed into the ſame Image, <hi>2 Cor. 3.18. 1 Joh. 3.2.</hi> and become one Spirit, <hi>1 Cor. 16, 17. Joh. 17.21.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>II.</hi> This was doubtleſs, <hi>the Principal Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment of Man</hi> in Innocence, is that to
<pb facs="tcp:152164:4"/>which he is to be reſtor'd in perfection, in his future State; and that for which he is to be prepared by exerciſe in this, which is his Principal Buſineſs here, the direct way to the one thing neceſſary, <hi>Luk. 10.42.</hi> the hidden Treaſure and Pearl of great price, <hi>Mat. 13.44.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>III.</hi> This of all things is moſt and principal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>oppoſed by the powers of Darkneſs,</hi> by all imaginable ſubtilty and efficacy, and great variety of Arts and Stratagems, both to <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert</hi> inconſiderate people from it, by pleaſure and Sports, and unprofitable Converſation under pretence of Civility, by ſundry inventions <hi>Eccl. 7.29.</hi> by the Pomps, and Vanities, and Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure, and Variety of impertinences of the world; by Cares and Anxieties, by Emulations, Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and differences with one another, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and to <hi>diſtract</hi> them in it by continual ſuggeſting unſeaſonable, impertinent and Evil thoughts and Fantaſies; or at leaſt to corrupt the Integrity and Purity of the Operation by ſelf reſpects: All which make it the more neceſſary to be very vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gilant and ſedulous in the Practice and Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of it.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>IV.</hi> It is not only <hi>practicable,</hi> but hath been eminently practiſed by the <hi>Patriarchs, who walked with God,</hi> Gen. <hi>5.24: 6.9.24.63.</hi> The Prophets of Old, and the Ancient Holy
<pb facs="tcp:152164:4"/>Chriſtian <hi>Eremites</hi> and Monks, and other de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout Chriſtians by <hi>Albertus</hi> himſelf, and in an high, and admirable manner, by <hi>Gregory Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pez</hi> and ſome other of later times; but may and <hi>ought to be ſtudied and practiſed</hi> by all ſorts of people, tho under different circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. By <hi>Young</hi> People, to fit and prepare them for Action in Buſineſs and Converſation; and by the <hi>Aged</hi> and ſuch as have ſufficiently acted their Part in the affairs of the World, to compleat their preparation for the next: By ſuch as have great <hi>Leiſure;</hi> people of Estates, who are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der no neceſſity of Labour; ſuch whoſe Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments require more of the Hand or Body, than of the mind, as many Artificers and People em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in Manufactures; by ſuch as have fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Intervals in their buſineſs, as many ſorts of Trades-men and others; and eſpecially by <hi>Students,</hi> and more eſpecially by ſuch as deſign the Sacred profeſſion, with good and honeſt minds; and by all, even the moſt buſie, at <hi>Times</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for Religious Employments, when awake in the Night, Morning and Evenings, and ſome portions of every day.</p>
            <p>And well diſpoſed minds will be often exert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Acts of this Nature, in the midſt of their moſt buſie Employments, and will find their bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs to ſucceed the better. The <hi>Labours of Albertus Magnus</hi> in his Reading and Study,
<pb facs="tcp:152164:5"/>in his publick Lectures and Diſputations, in his Office of Provincial, and afterwards of Biſhop, and in his Writings in Divinity, and all other Arts and Sciences, which in Print make one and twenty Volumes in Folio, were of themſelves almoſt incredible, and yet by what is atteſted upon their own Knowledge, by ſuch as were moſt converſant, and intimate with him, it ſeems that his conſtant Employments in Devotion, and Divine Contemplation were proportionable to the reſt, and indeed ſuch that the extraordinary progreſs which he made in thoſe, is imputed more to this; and to his Humility, than to all his Labour and Study beſides. And he himſelf in effect ſaith, or intimates as much, when he ſaith in general, <hi>Oratione &amp; Devotione plus ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiritur in Divinis Scientiis, quam Studio.</hi> And again, <hi>Divina, namque Sapientia im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>primitur nobis aſcendentious in Deum, &amp; ad ipſam Sapientiam.</hi> The like is reported of his Scholar <hi>Tho. Aquinas:</hi> And to mention no more, even in our own Age and Country, of the Learned Dr. <hi>Hammond,</hi> by the late Biſhop of <hi>Oxford,</hi> who wrote his Life; And I doubt not but many could atteſt the ſame of their own Knowledge and Experience, if they thought it fit.</p>
            <p>And certainly <hi>the Neglect</hi> of this in the Education of Youth <hi>in our Univerſities,</hi> is a
<pb facs="tcp:152164:5"/>principal Cauſe, that they have produced no more ſolid and ſubſtantial Fruit of later Ages, and that the Power of Religion is ſo much decayed in this Nation; for Learning without it is a Life<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs and Pernicious thing, as apt to diſtract the mind, as any other of the deceitful Delights of the World. The Neglect of this by ſuch as ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie themſelves with a Form of Religion, and employ more Time and Coſt to adorn their Bodies and their Houſes, than to cultivate their Souls, will prove a heavy Charge to a great Number of people one day, <hi>Luk. 13.24, 28. Mat. 25.8, 12.</hi> And they who have unhappily encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged the Neglect of Times appointed by Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, whether Divine or Humane, for Religious Employments, and the Profanation thereof, by Sports and Idleneſs, will then find whoſe Service they have therein promoted, and a diſmall Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count they have to Anſwer.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Author</hi> was one of the moſt Eminent Men of his Age, both for Learning and Piety, a zealous Man againſt all Vice and Wickedneſs, eſpecially of the Eccleſiaſticks, not ſparing the greateſt Prelates, and even the Popes themſelves, proving from the Scriptures, what great miſchiefs to the Church, and loſs of Souls proceeded from the miſcarriages of the Eccleſiaſticks. He was made Biſhop of <hi>Ratisbon</hi> ſore against his Will, by Pope <hi>Alexander IV.</hi> but would not remit
<pb facs="tcp:152164:6"/>his former Auſterities, nor leave off his mean Apparel, but viſited his Dioceſs on foot, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the ſecular buſineſs to truſty men, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied himſelf mholly to the care of his Flock and Divine Contemplation; and when <hi>Alexander</hi> was dead applied himſelf to his Succeſſor, and having obtain'd his leave, reſign'd his Biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick.</p>
            <p>This Little Book above forty Years ſince was by Sir <hi>Kenelm Digby</hi> thought worthy, not only of his peruſal, but pains, to turn it into Engliſh, and his Tranſlation, or rather, as he ſaith, Paraphraſe, was not long after Printed, with a Commendatory Preface to his Mother, but it came not to my hands, till this was in the Preſs, and beſides being out of Print, and a Paraphraſe, the ſtricter Tranſlation was thought fit to be Printed, and may poſſibly be more grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to ſome.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Socrates Chriſtianus.</signed>
            </closer>
            <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:152164:6"/>
            <head>A PREFACE to the two <hi>Treatiſes</hi> of Dr. <hi>John Staupitz.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>JOhn Staupitz,</hi> deſcended of a very Noble Family in <hi>Miſnia,</hi> was more Noble by his own Vertue, being an early and a great Proficient in Learning and Piety, and a great Favourer and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moter of both in others: and he wanted not advantages for it, being Abbot of St. <hi>Peters</hi> in <hi>Saltzburg,</hi> Vicar Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral of the Order of the <hi>Auguſtines</hi> in all <hi>Germany,</hi> and in great Eſteem with <hi>Frederick,</hi> Duke of <hi>Saxony,</hi> a Wiſe and Pious Prince, who made uſe of Him chiefly in the ordering of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity of <hi>Wirtemberg,</hi> which he founded in the Year <hi>1502.</hi> He it was who ſent for <hi>Martin Luther</hi> from <hi>Erford</hi> to this <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſity <hi>1508.</hi> having taken ſpecial notice of him for a Man of Parts, Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and Zeal for Religion, and <hi>15<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2.</hi> made him take the degree of Doctor. And <hi>Luther</hi> greatly eſteemed Him, always uſed to call Him his <hi>Staupitz,</hi> and often
<pb facs="tcp:152164:7"/>ſaid, He was a Great Man, and not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Learned and Eloquent in Schools and Churches, but alſo acceptable and vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable at Court, and amongſt great Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. He might have been preferred to the greatest Dignities, had he not induſtriouſly <hi>(ſtudio omni)</hi> avoided it. Though he was himſelf made Doctor <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>raram Eruditionem,</hi> yet was he no leſs ſtudious of the Practice than of the Knowledge of Divinity. And the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Year that <hi>Luther</hi> was made Doctor by his means, he ordered in all the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſteries, ſubject to his care, that the <hi>H. Scripture</hi> ſhould be read at Meals in the place of St. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> that the Friars might be better acquainted with them. And he it was who began the firſt moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>Reformation</hi> in the Year <hi>1517.</hi> For He was the Man who firſt complained againſt the Abuſes of the Preachers of <hi>Indulgencies,</hi> and reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving with all his might to oppoſe them, out of all his Friars, and all his Doctors in that <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity, made choice of <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> to preach againſt them, and gave
<pb facs="tcp:152164:7"/>him all the Encouragement and aſſiſtance he could afterwards; ſo that he was in truth the firſt Beginner of the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation.</p>
            <p>And though this alone was enough to recommend theſe Tracts of his to all Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, yet there are two Conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons more, which do not a little enhance the value of them: the one, that they are an Evidence of the Piety and Devotion of a Perſon ſo primarily concerned in the <hi>Reformation;</hi> which may ſerve to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the calumny, &amp; convince the uncha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritableneſs of thoſe Papiſts who would impute the beginning of the Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to an Emulation of the <hi>Auguſtines</hi> againſt the <hi>Dominicans,</hi> for Temporal Advantage: the other, that as in them may be obſerved the true Spirit of the firſt Reformers, ſo by them we both may perceive how much we are now degenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from their Piety and Devotion, and are admoniſhed and directed to return thereunto; which is the very End and Deſigns intended in the Tranſlation of theſe <hi>Authors.</hi> And therefore tho'
<pb facs="tcp:152164:8"/>this was none of thoſe antient Chriſtian who were firſt intended to be tranſlated yet is he ſo Primitive a Chriſtian in re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſpect of the Reformation, that he m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> very properly ſerve the Deſign as to the of the Reformed Churches; and no Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject can be more proper in order to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> end deſigned for all Chriſtians, that this which he treats.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>WHen this Book (Entitled, <hi>The Grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Duty of a Chriſtian</hi>) was printed the Tranſlator knew nothing of <hi>Joh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Staupitz</hi> the Author of the latter part o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> this Tranſlation, which being ſince m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> with, hath occaſioned the printing of thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Preface.</p>
            <p>The above-mentioned, and following Books, may be had at <hi>John Coughens</hi> in <hi>Plumtree-Court,</hi> near <hi>Fleet-Bridge,</hi> in <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourn.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Way to the Sab-bath of Reſt,</hi> Quarto By Mr. <hi>Tho. Bromley.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Mark of a true Chriſtian,</hi> or the <hi>Golden Rule of a Godly Life.</hi> Tranſlated out of <hi>High-Dutch.</hi> Octavo.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="rules">
            <pb facs="tcp:152164:8"/>
            <head>Some ſhort Rules of <hi>Chriſtian Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection,</hi> by <hi>Henricus Lovanienſis.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>HE who will be perfectly his Gods (given up to him) muſt obſerve <hi>Six things,</hi> whereof <hi>Three</hi> are <hi>External,</hi> and <hi>as many Internal.</hi> Of the <hi>External,</hi> the Firſt is, that his <hi>Clothes</hi> and his Exterior State be ſuch, whereby he may deſire to pleaſe none at all but God alone. Another is, that his <hi>Words</hi> be few, neceſſary, ſimple and concerning Divine things; the Third is, that his whole life, all his VVorks, and whatever he doth, be ſo compleat and blameleſs that in nothing he may be reprehended by any one.</p>
            <p>And of the Internal, the firſt is, that his <hi>Thoughts be pure</hi> and Heavenly, the Second, that he purely <hi>ſeek and intend God alone;</hi> the Third, that he be able eaſily and readily without any Trouble to bid farewel to all for God; that is, that whatever befalls him an <hi>Unmoveable, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſturbed and true Peace</hi> be in his mind, that <hi>as Water</hi> not moved with any blaſt of wind is quiet, ſo his Soul may in all things perſevere calm and immoveable. For as in water, ſo long as it ſwells with VVaves, and is ſtirr'd with continual motion, no man can behold himſelf, ſo that moſt ſimple, and moſt pure Good which is God, can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver direct the Rayes of his Light into his Soul, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Spirit or Interior part, ſo long as he is moved with proſperous, or advers occurrences. For, no Proſperity or Honour, tho never ſo great, for no
<pb facs="tcp:152164:9"/>Riches or Friends, or whatever fortunate accide<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> muſt our heart yield to Levity, Diſſoluteneſs, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> vain Joys. Again on the other ſide, he muſt per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                  <desc>••…</desc>
               </gap> undaunted and immoveable againſt all <hi>Adverſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> ſo that he be not diſturbed or hindred in his Sou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> by any damage done him, nor wiſh any Evil Withi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> or without, to any other, whatever he ſuffers from him; whether he deprive him of all his Good<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> whether Honour or Friends or Commodities, or a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> his comforts; yea tho he pull out his Eyes, fire <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Houſe, or whatever other miſchief he do him, h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> muſt by no means bear an Evil thought againſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> him, nor defire Revenge; but taking all, not from Man, but from the hand of God, render him devou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thanks, that he is in any thing made conformable to him. Yet notwithſtanding we muſt know, that there is none ſo happy or holy (Chriſt only and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Glorious Virgin excepted) but he may ſometimes ſuffer at leaſt the firſt motions of paſſion; for all the Saints have ſuffered them: But as ſoon as ever they perceived them, they knew how by the Grace of God ſo to ſuppreſs them, ſo as that they could not eaſily be perceived either in their Countenance, in their VVords, or their Geſtures.</p>
            <p>Laſtly to this Quiet <hi>(condition)</hi> this alſo is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that he be ſo affected, ſo diſpoſed, that tho he be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbered with <hi>Diverſity and multiplicity of buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> is ſoon as ever he turns himſelf to God in Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, no Image thereof, no appearance, not ſo much as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſhadow of it, may remain, whence in his Intellect or mind, he may become indiſpoſed or hindered. Our Lord Jeſus Christ. Grant that to theſe things we may all in time attain. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <div type="treatise">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:152164:10"/>
                  <head>A TREATISE OF <hi>Albertus Magnus;</hi> of adhering to God.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="chapter">
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> Of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ltimate and higheſt Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of Man, as far as the ſame is attainable in this Life.</head>
                     <p>I Have purpoſed with my ſelf, with the greateſt accuracy, (as far as it is poſſible in this our Exile and Pilgrim State) to give a deſcription of the Abſolute and Plenary Abſtraction from all things, and our ready, ſecure, naked, and firm adhering to our Lord God alone: And this the rather, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the very End of Chriſtian Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:152164:11"/>is Charity [or Divine Love,] where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we cleave to, [and are made one with] the Lord our God. To which Divine Adheſion by Love, every one is bound that hopes for Salvation, and is performed by the obſervance of the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts, and Conformity with the Will of God; the obſervance whereof, excludes whatſoever is repugnant to the Eſſence and Habit of Charity, ſuch as are all Mortal Sins. But thoſe that are in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Orders, have over and above this, bound themſelves to the Practice of Evangelical Perfection, and of thoſe things which are matter of Evangelical Councel and Advice, rather than ſtrict Impoſition, (and by means whereof we more readily arrive to our ultimate End, which is God; by the obſervance of which are likewiſe excluded all thoſe things, which clog and hinder the Activity and Fervor of Charity, from carrying us up into our Lord God;) ſuch as are the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying of all things, yea even of our own Soul and Body; for ſeeing that our Lord <hi>God is a Spirit, they that would worſhip him,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.24.</note> 
                        <hi>muſt do it in Spirit and in
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:152164:11"/>Truth;</hi> That is, with Knowledge and Love, with the Underſtanding and Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, devoid of all Phantaſms, or Images: To this purpoſe, is that Command of our Lord, <hi>But thou when thou Prayeſt,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Math.</hi> 6.6.</note> 
                        <hi>enter into thy Cloſet;</hi> that is, the inmoſt retreat of thy Heart; and when thou haſt ſhut thy door, <hi>viz.</hi> the door of thy Senſes upon thee; there do thou, with a Pure Heart, and Good Conſcience, and Faith unfeigned, <hi>pray to thy Father which is in Secret,</hi> in Spirit and in Truth. Which is then beſt done, when a Man being diſentangled and diveſted of all other things, and wholly retir'd within himſelf; and having forgot and ſhut out all, and every thing, in the Preſence of Jeſus Chriſt, the Mind alone doth in ſilence, with Faith and Aſſurance, lay open her Deſires, before her Lord God; and thus, by the entireſt Affection of her Heart and Love, doth moſt ſincerely and fully pour forth, and plunge her ſelf into God, with the inmoſt Marrow and Strength of all her Powers, dilating, inflaming, and diſſolving her ſelf wholly into him.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="4" facs="tcp:152164:12"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> How a Man may, deſpiſing all other things, adhere to, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend Chriſt alone.</head>
                     <p>NOw whoſoever Deſires, and makes it his Buſineſs to undertake and enter upon this State or kind of Life; it is needful that he, as it were, ſhutting his Eyes and Senſes, do not concern or trouble himſelf with, or be careful and ſollicitous about any thing whatſoever; but totally reject and renounce all things as impertinent, hurtful, and pernicious; and in the next place, that he wholly retire within himſelf, and in that Retire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, entertain no other Object, but Jeſus Chriſt alone, and him Crucified, and ſo preſs on through him, into him, <hi>i. e.</hi> through Man into God, through the Wounds of his Humanity, into the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt receſs of his Divinity; and there, without any further diſputing, readily and ſecurely commit himſelf and all his
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:152164:12"/>Concerns to his indefatigable Providence, according to that of St. <hi>Peter, Caſting all your care upon him,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.7.</note> who can do all. And again, <hi>Be ſollicitous for nothing.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Phil.</hi> 4 6.</note> And that of the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Caſt thy care upon the Lord,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pſ.</hi> 55.22.</note> 
                        <hi>and he ſhall ſuſtain thee:</hi> And again, <hi>But it is good for me to,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pſ.</hi> 73.28.</note> 
                        <hi>cleave unto God:</hi> And again, <hi>I have ſet the Lord always before me:</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pſ.</hi> 16.8.</note> And with the Spouſe in the Canticles,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Cant.</hi> 3.4.</note> 
                        <hi>I have found him whom my Soul loveth;</hi> becauſe,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Wiſd.</hi> 7.11.</note> as <hi>Wiſdom</hi> ſaith, <hi>All good things come together with it.</hi> This is that hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Heavenly <hi>Treaſure, and that precious Pearl</hi> which cannot be purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.44, 5, 6.</note> but by the parting with all that we have, which being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred before all, in the Strength of the Spirit is to be ſought for with humble Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence, moſt inſtant Endeavours, and quiet Silence, even to the loſs of all outward Conveniencies and Advantages of Praiſe or Honour, in the Strength of the Spirit.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:152164:13"/>For what Advantage will it be to one that hath dedicated himſelf to God, if he gain the whole World, but at the ſame time ſuffer loſs in his Soul? Or of what profit is the higheſt Profeſſion of Religion, or a ſeeming Holy Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, without living in the Spirit of Truth and Humility, wherein Chriſt dwells, through Faith wrought and form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Love; wherefore we are told that <hi>the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God is within us:</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Luke</hi> 17.21.</note> which is no other than Jeſus Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="7" facs="tcp:152164:13"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Wherein the Perfection of Man, in this Life, doth conſiſt.</head>
                     <p>SUre it is that the more ſollicitouſly buſie the mind is in thinking and managing theſe Inferiour and Humane Affairs, at the greater diſtance it puts it ſelf from Superiour and Heavenly Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, and true inward Devotion; and on the contrary, the more fervently ſhe recollects her ſelf from the Memory, Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, and Underſtanding of things here below, and betakes her ſelf to thoſe above, the more perfect will her Prayer be, and the more pure her Contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; becauſe it is impoſſible ſhe ſhould be perfectly intent on both theſe together, they being as oppoſite as Light and Darkneſs. For he that cleaves to God, is, and walks in the Light, but he that ſticks to the World, gropes in the Dark.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:152164:14"/>Whence the moſt ſublime Perfection of Man in this Life is this, to be ſo far u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited to God, that his whole Soul, with all its Powers and Faculties, be to that degree gathered up into the Lord his God, that he may become one Spirit with him, ſo as to <hi>Remember</hi> nothing but God, to feel or <hi>Underſtand</hi> nothing but God; and that all his <hi>Affections</hi> being u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited and centred in the Joys of Love, may ſweetly repoſe in the ſole Fruition of their Creator. For the Image of God impreſs'd on the Soul, conſiſts in theſe three Faculties, <hi>viz.</hi> Reaſon, Memory, and Will: And as long as theſe do not wholly receive their Stamp and Impreſs from God, the Soul is not Deiform, according to the intent and ſcope of its firſt Creation. For God is the form of the Soul, by whom the Soul muſt be impreſs'd, as the Wax is by the Seal. Now this can never be fully per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, until Reaſon be, according to its capacity, perfectly illuminated with the knowledge of God, who is the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign <hi>Truth;</hi> and the <hi>Will</hi> be perfectly bent and taken up, in loving the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme <hi>Good;</hi> and the <hi>Memory</hi> be wholly
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:152164:14"/>employ'd in the beholding and enjoying of Eternal Happineſs, and in a ſweet and delightful Repoſe and Acquieſcence in the ſame. And foraſmuch as in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummate Poſſeſſion of theſe, conſiſts the Glory of the Bliſs of Heaven, it is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent that the true beginning and antici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation of theſe, is the Perfection of this Life.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="chapter">
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> How the Activity of Man ought to be in the Intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect alone, and not in the Senſes.</head>
                     <p>HAppy therefore is the Man, who by a continual effacing of all Phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſms and imaginary Repreſentations, and by Introverſion, and the lifting up his
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:152164:15"/>mind into God, doth at laſt, in a man<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner forget and leave behind him all I mages, and by this means, conſequently operating inwardly with a Naked, Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and pure Intellect and Affection, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the moſt Pure and Simple Object, God. Wherefore thou muſt reject and caſt out of thy mind all Phantaſms, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentations, and Images, and the forms of all things beſides God, to the end that thy whole Exerciſe about God within thee may depend only of thy naked In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellect, Affection, and Will. For indeed, the true End of all thy holy Exerciſes is this, that thou do intend and repoſe in the Lord God within thee, by the pureſt Act of Intellection, and the devouteſt Affection, without all Repreſentations or Intanglements whatſoever. Now this Exerciſe cannot be diſcharged by any corporal Organs, or the external Senſes, but by that part in Man, by which he is Man: Now that which conſtitutes a Man, is Underſtanding and Love. And therefore as long as Man ſports it with his Imagination and Senſes, and fixeth there, he is not yet got beyond the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Bounds of his Beſtial Nature,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:152164:15"/>that is, of that part within him, which he hath common with Brute Beaſts; foraſmuch as they do perceive, and are affected with ſuch ſenſible Repreſentations, and no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, becauſe the power of their Soul reacheth no higher. But the caſe is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe with Man, who is Created in the Image of God, according to his Intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, Affection, and Free-will, which muſt be immediately, purely, and naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly impreſt by God, and become united, and firmly cleave unto him. Wherefore alſo the Devil doth with all poſſible dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence endeavour to hinder and diſturb this Exerciſe, as far as in him lies, foraſmuch as he knows it to be an Entrance and Anticipation of Eternal Life; which makes him to envy ſo great a Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to Man. For which reaſon he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways endeavours to eſtrange and alienate the mind of Man from his Lord God, ſometimes by one Temptation, ſometimes by another; ſometimes by one Paſſion, and ſometimes by another; ſometimes by ſuperfluous ſolicitouſneſs, and indiſcreet carking; ſometimes by Diſturbance, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Converſation, and unreaſonable Curioſity; ſometimes by the ſtudy of cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:152164:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>and ſubtile Writings, impertinent Diſcourſes, Reports, and News; ſometimes by Adverſity, and ſometimes by Proſperity. Which though ſometimes they may ſeem to us to be very light, and in a manner, no Sins at all, are, nevertheleſs, great lets and hindrances to this holy Exerciſe and Work. And therefore, however they may repreſent themſelves to us as profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table and neceſſary, yet are immediately to be rejected and diſowned, as hurtful and pernicious, whether they be ſmall or great, and to be wholly expelled and caſt out of our Senſes. Accordingly it is highly neceſſary that all things heard, ſeen, done, or ſpoken, and other ſuch like, be received by us without any Phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſms [Images] or dwelling upon them; and that neither afterwards, nor before, nor at the perceiving of them, we do form of feed any Repreſentations; and when thus a Phantaſm does not enter the Memory and the Mind, then can it neither hinder a Man in his Prayer, Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſinging of Pſalms, or in any other Spiritual Operation or Exerciſe whatſoever; neither will it ever again obviate and diſturb him. Thus do thou
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:152164:16"/>readily and ſecurely commit thy whole ſelf, and all, and every one of thy Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns in ſilence and reſt to the infallible and moſt certain Providence and wiſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſal of the Divine Majeſty, who himſelf will appear for thee in this Combate, and fight for thee, and will with more Honour and Sweetneſs deliver and comfort thee, than if thou ſhould'ſt continually, night and day, hammer upon the Anvil of thy thoughts and Imagination about it; and with a vain, vagabond, and yet cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiv'd Mind, fooliſhly run up and down from one contrivance to another, ſpending thy precious time in tireing thy Mind and Body, and fooliſhly conſuming the ſtrength of them both. Wherefore do thou receive all, and every thing, whenſoever or howſoever they come up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thee, with an even temper, in ſilence and tranquility, as reach'd forth to thee by the hand of the Paternal Divine Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence. Diveſt therefore thy ſelf of the Images and Phantaſms of all Bodily things, according to the Exigence of thy State and Profeſſion, that with a naked and ſimplified mind, thou may'ſt ſincere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cleave to him, to whom thou haſt
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:152164:17"/>ſo frequently and entirely devoted thy ſelf, that there may be nothing to medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate or interpoſe between thy Soul and him, that ſo with a pure and fixed view, thou mayeſt raiſe thy ſelf from the Wounds of his Manhood, into the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Light and Charity of his God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="chapter">
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Concerning Purity of Heart, which is to be endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed above, and before all things.</head>
                     <p>IF ſo be therefore, thou doſt deſire and endeavour, by a ſtrait, ſafe and ſhort path, to arrive to the end of true Bliſs, here and hereafter, of Grace and Glory, then do thou with an intent mind, ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly aſpire after continual cleanneſs of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:152164:17"/>Heart and Purity of Mind, with a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant calm and tranquillity of thy Senſes, and recollecting the Affections of thy Heart, continually fix them above, on the Lord thy God, withdrawing thy ſelf in the mean time from thy Familiars and Acquaintance, and, as far as lies in thee, from all Men, and from all things that might be a let or hindrance to thy holy purpoſe; alwaies watching an Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity where and when thou may'ſt find place and time, for ſweet reſt and contemplation, and the enjoyment of the ſecret Pleaſures of Silence, avoiding the ſhipwracks of this preſent World, and the noiſe, hurry, and confuſion of it. Wherefore let this be thy chief Study at all times, how thou may'ſt attain to Clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Purity, and Reſt of Heart, that ſo continually, having ſhut the doors of thy Carnal Senſes, thou may'ſt turn into thy ſelf, and lock up thy Heart, as far as is poſſible, from the Repreſentations of all Senſible things, and the Imaginations of Earthly Objects. It is this Purity of Heart that excels all Spiritual Exerciſes whatſoever, as being the final Intention, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>, and Reward for all the Labours
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:152164:18"/>which a Religious and Spiritual Man takes in this Life. Wherefore do thou with all Diligence, Application, and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour, rid thy Heart, Senſes and Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections from all theſe things that may impede its Freedom, and from every other Concern of the World, that hath the leaſt Power to Allure, Bind, and Captivate thee. And ſo ſtrive to recol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect and gather up all the wandring ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſions of thy Heart, and all the Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of thy Mind, into that One, True, Simple, and Supreme Good, and to keep them alwaies recollected within thy ſelf, as in one place; and by this means endeavour alwaies to cleave with thy mind to God and Divine things, and leaving thy Earthly Frailty behind, ſtrive to transform thy ſelf continually into the pattern of the Heavenly things, through thy inward Communion with, and retirement into Jeſus Chriſt. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if thou makeſt it thy Buſineſs to ſtrip and purifie thy ſelf from all Images and Repreſentations, and with Truſt and Confidence, to ſimplifie and quiet thy Heart and Mind in the Lord thy God, that thou may'ſt feel, and take in the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:152164:18"/>Fountain of the Divine Good Pleaſure in all thy inward parts, and by thy good will be united to God, in thy Intellect or Underſtanding, this Exerciſe alone will be ſufficient for thee, and ſerve inſtead of all Study and Reading of the Holy Scriptures, and will advance thee to the Love of God and thy Neighbour, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as the Anointing Teacheth thee. Wherefore with all Study, do thou labour and endeavour to ſimplifie thy Heart, that being immoveable, and at peace from any intruding vain Phantaſms, thou may'ſt always turn thy ſelf to, and ſtand faſt in the Lord, within thee, to that degree, as if thy Soul was got into the always preſent <hi>NOW</hi> of Eternity, that is, of the Deity; in ſuch a manner, that for the Love of Jeſus Chriſt, from a Pure Heart, a Good Conſcience, and Faith unfeigned, thou may'ſt wholy for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake and leave thy ſelf, and entirely and fully commit thy whole ſelf to God in all Tribulation and every Event whatſoever, always deſiring to be patiently reſign'd and obedient to his Will and Good Pleaſure.</p>
                     <p>Now to the end, that thou may'ſt come to this State, it is neceſſary for thee, fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:152164:19"/>to return to thine own Heart, and to abide there; ridding thy ſelf, as far as is poſſible, of all things, preſerving the Eye of thy Mind continually in Purity and Reſt, voiding thy Intellect of all Images and Repreſentations of inferiour things, ſetting free the Affection of thy Will from all Earthly Cares, and with a fervent Love, from the very bottom and root of thy Soul, cleaving to the True Supreme Good, having thy Memory alſo continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally lifted upwards, and firmly fix'd and grounded in the ſame alone True Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign, Eſſential, and Uncreated Good, to the end, that thy whole Soul, with all its Powers and Faculties, being thus gather'd up into God, may become one Spirit with him, which is the higheſt Perfection at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainable in this Life. It is this Unity of Spirit and Love, whereby Man is made conform in all his Deſires and Wiſhes with the Supreme and Eternal Will, ſo as that he becomes that by Grace, which God is by Nature. And here we are to obſerve, that in that very moment wherein any Man by the Grace of God overcomes his own Will, that is his inordinate Love and Likeing, ſo as to dare fully and totally truſt
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:152164:19"/>the Lord God with all his Needs and Concerns, he does ſo highly pleaſe God, that he freely beſtows upon him ſuch a degree of Grace, by which he feels that true Charity and Love begot in him, which expels all doubts and fears, and gives him a ſure and confident hope in God. Wherefore nothing can he more happy or advantageous for us, than to caſt our All upon him, in whom there is no want. And ſeeing that as long as thou ſtandeſt in thy ſelf, thou doſt not ſtand faſt, caſt thy whole ſelf ſecurely upon God, and he will take thee up, heal thee and ſave thee. If thou doff but continually revolve theſe things in thy Mind, thou wilt find them more conducive to a truly Happy Life, than all the Riches, Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, Profits, and Honours, yea and all the ſuppoſed Wiſdom and Knowledge to boot, of this deceiving and corruptible World, yea, tho' thou ſhouldſt excel in all theſe, all that ever were before thee.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:152164:20"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> That we muſt cleave to God with a naked Intellect and Affection.</head>
                     <p>WHerefore ſeeing that by how much the more thou ſhalt empty thy ſelf of all Images, and External, Worldly, and Senſible Intanglements, by ſo much the more thy Soul will recover its Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Strength and Vigour, and the uſe of its internal Senſes to perceive and reliſh thoſe things that are above; do thou en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to quit all Phantaſms and ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginary Repreſentations of Bodily Things, becauſe nothing is more pleaſing and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to God, than a Mind diveſted of all ſuch like Forms and Images, for his Delights are with the Sons of Men, that is ſuch, who with a Calm Mind, Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified, and Simplified from all theſe Occupations, Diſtractions, and Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, do intend, apply, and cleave to him, making this their whole buſineſs. For otherwiſe if thy Memory, Imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and Thoughts be often buſied a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:152164:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>theſe things, it muſt needs be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veigled, either with ſome new things, or the remains of ſome formerly entertained, or be variouſly affected and diſtracted with other occurring Objects,<note place="margin">Wiſd. 1.5.</note> 
                        <hi>For the holy Spirit of Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline</hi> (as the Wiſe Man ſaith) <hi>removes its ſelf from thoughts that are without Underſtanding.</hi> Wherefore a true Lover of Jeſus Chriſt, muſt be ſo u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited in his Intellect, through good Will, to the Divine Will and Goodneſs, and be ſo naked and ſtript of all Phantaſms and Paſſions, as not ſo much as to take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice whether he be derided and flouted at, or Loved and Honoured, or whether any thing elſe happen to him. For a good Will makes up all, and is above and beyond all: Wherefore if there be a good Will, and that the ſame in the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellect be purely conform and united to God, it can do no hurt, tho' the Fleſh or Senſuality and the outward Man ſhould incline to Sin, and be backward and dead to that which is good; yea, even though the inward Man alſo, ſhould be dead and liſtleſs to any thing of Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; for in this caſe it is ſufficient for a
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:152164:21"/>Man by Faith and good Will, nakedly to cleave to God in the Intellect or Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme part of the Soul.</p>
                     <p>And this he will do, if he throughly perceive and be ſenſible of his own im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfection and nothingneſs, and know that all his good conſiſts, and is in his Creator; and if with all his Powers and Faculties he abandon himſelf and all Creatures, and totally plunge his whole ſelf into his Creator, ſo as to direct all his Actions purely and entirely to his Lord God, as the ſole end and ſcope of them all, ſeeking nor deſiring any thing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides him, in whom he perceives himſelf to have found all Good, with all Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Perfection. And by this proceſs he becomes in a manner transformed into God, to that degree, that he can neither think, nor underſtand, nor love, nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member any thing but God, and the things of God; nor doth he ſee himſelf, and other Creatures, ſave only in God; Neither doth he love any thing ſave God alone, nor remember or make mention of them or of himſelf, but in God. Now this knowledge of the Truth makes a Soul very humble, judging it
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:152164:21"/>ſelf, but not another; whereas on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, the Worldly Wiſdom makes the Soul proud, Vain, Arrogant, and pufft up with Wind. Let us lay down this therefore for a Spiritual and Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Doctrine; that he who would draw near to the Knowledge, Service, and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarity or Communion with God, and that would really poſſeſs him, muſt of neceſſity wholly ſtrip and diveſt his Heart from all ſenſible Love, not only of every Perſon whatſoever, but of every Creature; to the end, that with a ſimple and entire Heart he may reach forward and preſs into the Lord God his Creator, freely without all Duplicity, Care, or Sollicitouſneſs, with a full aſſured Truſt and Confidence in his Providence, as to all his Concerns.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:152164:22"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> How the Heart is to be gathered up, or recollected into it ſelf.</head>
                     <p>MOREOVER, as it is ſaid in the Book of <hi>the Spirit and Soul,</hi> Chapter 21. <hi>To mount up to God, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> to enter into ones ſelf.</hi> For he who in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly entring, and intimately pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trating into himſelf, gets above or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond himſelf, he truly mounts up to God. Let us therefore gather up our Hearts from the various Diſtractions o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> this World, and recall them to the joy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> within, that we may at laſt be able to fix them in the light of Divine Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation. For this is the true Life and Reſt of our Heart, when by Deſire it is fix'd in the Love of God, and ſweetly refreſh'd with his Divine Comfort. But the reaſon why in the experimental taſte and reliſh hereof we are manifoldly hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, ſo as that we can by no means reach to him, is plainly this, becauſe the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:152164:22"/>Mind of Man being diſtracted with ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitouſneſs, doth not enter into it ſelf by the <hi>Memory;</hi> being overſhadowed (clouded) with Phantaſms, doth not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire into her ſelf through the <hi>Intellect,</hi> being allur'd by Luſts and Concupiſcence, doth not turn in to her ſelf, through the deſire of internal ſweetneſs, and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual joys; and being thus wholly ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken up with theſe ſenſible and preſent Things, ſhe can never enter in to her ſelf, <hi>viz,</hi> the Image of God, in her ſelf. It behoveth therefore above all things, and is neceſſary, that with humble Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, and great Confidence, the Mind raiſe it ſelf, above it ſelf, and every Creature, by a total denying and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing of them all; and ſay within her ſelf, he whom of all things, before all things, and above all things I ſeek, love, long for, and deſire, is neither ſenſible, nor imaginable, but above e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very thing that is ſenſible and intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gible too: He is not to be perceived by any ſence, but wholly deſirable by full and perfect deſire; neither is he figura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, or repreſentable, but to be moſt perfectly long'd for, by the moſt inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:152164:23"/>affection: He is not to be rated, or valued, but wholly to be affected with a pure heart, as being above all things amiable, and delectable; and of infinite Goodneſs, and Perfection. And thus ſhe is carried into the darkneſs of the Mind, and becomes higher raiſed within her ſelf, and enters deeper into her ſelf. And this manner of aſcending to the Aenigmatical, or obſcure Viſion of the moſt Holy Trinity in Unity, and Unity in Trinity, in Jeſu Chriſt, is by ſo much the more fervent, by how much the power of Elevation is more intimate to the mind, and ſo much the more fruitful and profitable, by how much it is nearer, and ſtronger in Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection. For in Spiritual Things, thoſe are accounted higher, which are more inward, as to Spiritual Experience. Wherefore, do thou never leave, never reſt, until thou get a taſte of ſome Pledges or foretaſtes of the fulneſs that is to come; and 'till thou per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the ſweetneſs of the Divine Loveli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, by ſome little firſt Fruits; and do not ceaſe running after her in the perfume of her good Ointments, unti
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:152164:23"/>thou come to ſee the God of Gods in <hi>Sion.</hi> For, in thy Spiritual Progreſs, and in this Union with, and cleaving to God within thy ſelf, thou muſt neither deſiſt, nor give back, until thou haſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained what thou lookeſt for; whereof, we may take an Example from thoſe who are going up an high Hill: For if in this aſcent our Spirit through Luſt and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, comes to plunge it ſelf into the Tranſitory Things here below, it im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately is led out of the way, by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Diſtractions, and crooked wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Paths; and being manifoldly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided, is ſcatter'd in it ſelf, according to the multiplicity of the Objects its Concupiſcence deſires: Whence neceſſary follows Motion without ſteadineſs, Run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning without attaining, and Labour without Reſt. But, if on the other ſide, our Heart and Spirit do withdraw it ſelf by Deſire and Love from the infinite diſtraction of inferior Things here below, wholly quitting them, and by little and little gathering up her ſelf into that one Unchangeable, All-ſufficient Good, learn and accuſtom her ſelf to ſtay at home, and with her
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:152164:24"/>whole affection do inſeparably cleave un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it; ſo much the more ſhe is gathered up into one, and fortified, by how much ſhe is elevated by underſtanding, and deſire to the Things that are above; and becomes ſo habitually fixed and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed in the true Supream Good with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in her ſelf, 'till at length, ſhe be made altogether immutable, and arrive to that true Life, which is the Lord God himſelf; ſo as that perpetually, without any viciſſitude of Change, or Time, ſhe now repoſeth her ſelf in that inward Quiet, and ſecret Manſion of the Deity; being perfectly fix'd and ſetled within her ſelf, in <hi>Chriſt Jeſus, who is the Way,</hi> to thoſe that come to him,<note place="margin">John 14.6.</note> 
                        <hi>the Truth, and the Life.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="chapter">
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> How a Devout Perſon muſt Commit himſelf to God in all Events, and in all his Concerns.</head>
                     <p>I Suppoſe, that from what hath been already ſaid, thou doſt perceive that the more thou ſhalt diveſt thy ſelf from
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:152164:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>Images, and all Worldly and Created Things, and by Good Will be united in thy Intellect to God, the nearer thou wilt approach to the State of Innocence, and Perfection. Than which, what can be conceived better, more happy, or more delightful? To which purpoſe, nothing can be of more avail, than that thou keep thy mind naked of all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Phantaſms, and Images, and from all Intanglements whatſoever, ſo as not to be concerned, or trouble thy ſelf, neither about the World, nor about Friends, or Relations, nor about Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity, or Adverſity; neither about any thing paſt, preſent, or to come, either in thy ſelf, or in others: No, nor over much about thine own Sins; but with a certain pure ſimplicity, ſuppoſe thy ſelf to be naked, and alone with God, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the World; for if thy Soul were already launched into Eternity, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated from the Body, ſurely it would not be buſied about Secular Matters, nor would it be concern'd about the courſe of the World, neither about Peace, nor War; fair, or foul weather, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Temporal Thing, but would uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formly,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:152164:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>and totally intend, be at leiſure for, and cleave to God alone: In like manner, do thou now (according to the preſent poſſibility) leave thy Body, and all Creatures preſent, and to come, and ſteadily fix the view of thy Mind and Spirit, according to thy utmoſt power, nakedly and readily upon that increated Light, that thy Spirit may be ſo ſtript and diveſted from all Phantaſms, and from all Intanglements, and clowdy over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhadowings, as may be ſuppos'd that of an Angel tyed to a Body, who is not hindred by the activity of the Fleſh, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is intangled with vain and hurrying Thoughts. Let thy Spirit therefore for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie it ſelf againſt all Temptations, Vexations, Injuries, and Affronts what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever; ſo that with the greateſt uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernedneſs, and evenneſs of Temper, it may immoveably perſevere in God, in Adverſity, as well as Proſperity. And when any thing of trouble, liſtleſſneſs to any thing that is good, or confuſion of Mind, do chance to ſeize thee, do not thou therefore think ſtrange, or be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged; neither run thou, upon this account, to vocal Prayers, or other ways
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:152164:25"/>of comfort: but let this only be thy ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe, that thou awaken and ſtir up thy ſelf through good will in the Intellect, that ſo thou mayſt cleave to God with thy mind, whether thy ſenſual Part will or not. For, a Devout and truly Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Soul ought to be ſo intimately united to God, and to have, and make his Will ſo conform to the Divine Will, that it may not buſie it ſelf with, nor cleave to any Creature whatſoever, any more than ſhe did before ſhe was Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; and as if there were nothing at all beſides God and the Soul; and that it may with an even temper take all and every thing that happens to it, ſecurely, and infallibly, from the gracious hand of the Divine Providence in all things, uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formly ſuffering the Lord, in Patience, Tranquility, and Silence. Wherefore it appears, that to ſtrip the mind of all Phantaſms, doth above any other Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe whatſoever, avail and conduce to a Spiritual Life, in which, by good will, thou mayſt be united to, and become like to God, in thy intellect. For by this means, there will be nothing to me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate, or intervene betwixt thee and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:152164:26"/>God. Conſider therefore, how greatly thou doſt degenerate from the Nobility of thy Being, and how highly thou Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt againſt the Lord thy God, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all his Righteouſneſs, if thou with thy Will and Love do cleave unto the Creature, rather than to the Creator; by this means, preferring the Creature, before the Creator.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="chapter">
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> That Divine Contemplation is to be preferr'd before all other Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Exerciſes whatſoever.</head>
                     <p>FOraſmuch therefore as all things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides God, are the Effect and Work of the Creator, having their Power and Being, and whatſoever they are or can, ſtinted and limited; and as at firſt they were produc'd out of Nothing, ſo are ſtill ſurrounded with nullities, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thingneſs, and of themſelves tend to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; it follows, that they muſt neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily, every moment receive their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtence, conſervation, activity, and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:152164:26"/>elſe may be in them, from the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign Workman God, as being in, and of themſelves, inſufficient for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and others; to whoſe Divine Working they being compared, have the ſame proportion, as Nothing to Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, or a Finite thing to that which is Infinite. Wherefore, let all our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation, Life, and Operation, be in him alone, and about him, and for him, and to him; who, with one hint of his Will, is able, and knows to produce things infinitely more perfect than thoſe Creatures we now ſee. There can be therefore, neither with reſpect to the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellect, or to the Will, any Contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Fruition of Love more profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, perfect, happy, and delightful, than that which hath for its Object the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, the true and Soveraign Good; from whom, in whom, through whom, and to whom are all things; who alone is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely ſufficient for himſelf, and all things: Who, moſt ſimply, fully, and ſupereminently contains, and has concen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred in himſelf from Eternity, the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of all things, in whom there is nothing that is not himſelf; with whom,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:152164:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>and through whom, the Cauſes of all unſtable things have their laſting ſubſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtence, and eſtabliſhment: In whom are the Immutable Ideas and Principles of all Mutable Things, and in whom the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Reaſons of all Rational, and Irrational, and Temporal Things do live for ever; who fulfills all, and eſſentially fills all and every thing with himſelf; and who is more intimately preſent by his Eſſence to every thing, than the thing is to it ſelf; in whom all things are united and one, and in whom they live Eternally. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, if by reaſon of weakneſs, or the unaccuſtomedneſs of the underſtanding, any Man be oblig'd to Meditate, or Contemplate on the Creatures, then this will be the beſt, trueſt, and moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable way for him; that at leaſt in all his Contemplations, and Meditations, whether about Creatures, or about the Creator, a delight in the Creator him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, the One and Trine God, may ariſe within him; and that the fire of Divine Love and true Life may thence flame forth in himſelf, and in others, for the obtaining of Eternal Felicity. And here we may obſerve the difference there is between
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:152164:27"/>the Contemplation of Chriſtian Believers; and that of the Heathen Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers: For the Contemplation of Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers is intended only for the perfection of the Contemplator, and therefore ſtops in the underſtanding, and ſo their end herein, is intellectual Knowledge. But the Contemplation of the Saints, is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken up for the Love of him whom they Contemplation, that is, of God; and therefore does not ſtop in the Intellect by Knowledge, as in its ultimate end; but paſſeth over into the affection by Love. Wherefore the Saints in their Contemplation, have the Love of God for their principal end, and aim; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is far more happy and bliſsful to know and have the Lord Jeſus Chriſt Spiritually by Grace, than without Grace, corporally, or eſſentially. Now whilſt the Soul thus abſtracts it ſelf from all things, and reflects into it ſelf, the eye of Contemplation by this means be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes dilated, and raiſeth it ſelf like a Ladder, whereby ſhe mounts to the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of God. From which beholding, the Soul becomes inflamed with the Love of Coeleſtial, and Divine Good
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:152164:28"/>Things; and looks upon all Temporal Things aloof, as if they were juſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. Thus, when we draw near to God by the way of Negation, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moving from him all that is perceptible, or comprehenſible; in the firſt place, we remove from him all that is Bodily, Senſible, or Imaginable; in the next place, all that is Intelligible, and laſt of of all, Eſſence, or Being it ſelf, as it is in the Creatures. And by this means, according to St. <hi>Dionyſius</hi> the <hi>Areopagite,</hi> we approach neareſt to the Divine Eſſence, and are in the <hi>ready way of being joyn'd to him.</hi> And this is <hi>that thick Darkneſs, where God is ſaid to dwell;</hi> and <hi>into which</hi> Moſes <hi>entred,</hi> and through it paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to his <hi>inacceſſible Light.</hi> But <hi>that which is Spiritual is not firſt, but that which is Animal;</hi> ſo that according to the natural and accuſtomed Order, we are to proceed from the Labour of Action, to the Reſt of Contemplation; and from the Moral Virtues, to the Theorical, and Speculative. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, O my Soul, why is it that thou buſieſt thy ſelf to no purpoſe, about the many vain and ſuperfluous Things where
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:152164:28"/>thou art always in want? And doſt not rather fix thy intention and love upon that one Beſt and Soveraign Good, which contains all Good, and is only ſufficient for thee, and all things? Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy therefore, yea thrice unhappy he, who knows, and has all things beſides him, but is ignorant of him. For if a Man ſhould be ſuppoſed to know all things, and him, yet would not he be the happier for knowing them, but him only; whence St. <hi>John</hi> tells us, and <hi>this is Life Eternal,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Joh. 17. v. 3. Pſalm. 17. v. 15.</note> 
                        <hi>that they know thee the only true God,</hi> &amp;c. And the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt, <hi>I ſhall be ſatisfied at the appearance of thy Glory,</hi> or accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the <hi>Hebrew,</hi> when thy image, or likeneſs ſhall awake in me.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="chapter">
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. X.</hi> Actual and ſenſible Devotion is not ſo much to be minded, as the adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, or cleaving to God with our Will.</head>
                     <p>MOreover, do not thou greatly mind actual Devotion, ſenſible ſweetneſs, or tears; but let it ſuffice thee
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:152164:29"/>to be by good will in thy intellect, with thy Mind united to God, within thy ſelf, foraſmuch as nothing is more pleaſing to God, than a Mind ſtrip'd naked of Phantaſms, Images, and Repteſentations of the Creatures. It becomes therefore a truly devout Perſon, to eſtrange himſelf from all Creatures, that he may nakedly, and readily intend, apply himſelf, and adhere to God alone, within himſelf. Wherefore deny thy ſelf, that thou mayeſt nakedly follow Chriſt thy Lord God, who being truly Poor, Obedient, and Chaſt, humbled himſelf, and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered for us, and at whoſe Life and Death many were greatly offended, as appears from the Hiſtory of the Goſpel. Now as we ſee that a Soul ſeparate from its Body, doth not mind, or take notice what becomes of it, whether it be burnt, hang'd, abus'd, or curſed; and is not at all troubled or grieved for any injuries that are done to it; but has all its thoughts fixed upon that ever preſent <hi>Now</hi> of Eternity, and the <hi>one thing ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary</hi> our Saviour ſpeaks of in the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel; In like manner be thou alſo af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected to thy Body, being ſo unconcern'd
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:152164:29"/>with it, as if thou waſt already out of the Body, and have always thy mind fixed upon the Eternity of thy Soul in God, and earneſtly direct and level thy thoughts at that one thing, of which Chriſt ſaith, <hi>But one thing is needful:</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Luke</hi> 10.42.</note> and by this means thou wilt feel great incomes, and aſſiſtance of Grace, for the attainment of true nakedneſs of Mind, and ſimplification of Heart. And moſt certain it is, that this <hi>one thing,</hi> is moſt preſent to thee, and will appear ſo, as ſoon as thou ſhalt have rid thy ſelf from thy imaginary repreſentations, and all other intanglements; and thou wilt ſoon find, that now thou canſt with a naked, free, and ready mind apply thy ſelf, and cleave to God; and by this means thou ſhalt be invincible in all things what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever that can happen to thee, as the Holy Martyrs, Fathers, and all the Elect and Bleſſed Saints were; who deſpiſing and rejecting all things, only minded the Eternal Salvation of their Souls in God: And being thus armed within, and united to God by Good will, they contemned all the Things of the World,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:152164:30"/>even as if their Souls already had been actually ſeparated from their Bodies.</p>
                     <p>Conſider well therefore, how great the power is of a good will united to God; yea, how by this impreſſion of God upon the Soul, as by its virtual and ſpiritual Diviſion from the Fleſh, the Soul comes to look upon the outward Man as if it were none of hers; and is ſo unconcern'd at any thing that is done to it, or its fleſh, as if they were done to another Body; for <hi>he that cleaves to God, becomes one Spirit with him.</hi> Wherefore do thou never dare in the leaſt to think or imagine any thing in the preſence of the Lord thy God within thee, which thou wouldeſt bluſh that Men ſhould hear, or ſee; and that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the higheſt Reverence which is due to the Divine Majeſty, in his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Temple. It is alſo fit and juſt, that all thy thoughts be erect and lifted up to God alone; and that the view of thy mind be fixed only upon him, as if there were nothing at all beſides him, and by cloſe cleaving unto him, enjoy him, which is a perfect Commencement and Anticipation of the Life to come.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="11" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="41" facs="tcp:152164:30"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. XI.</hi> How we are to reſiſt Temptations, and to bear Tribulations.</head>
                     <p>THere is no man that draws near to God with a true and ſincere heart, but he muſt expect to be tried, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved with manifold Vexations, and Temptations. Now in all Temptations let this Precept be obſerved; that when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever thou feeleſt any Temptation, that thou do not aſſent to it, and that thou bear it patiently, and quietly, with hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, and long ſufferance. And if they chance to be Blaſphemous and Fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy injections, take it for a certain Rule, that there is no way better to overcome and be rid of them, than by deſpiſing them, though they be never ſo horrible, filthy, and abominable Blaſphemies; let this be thy ſole Armour of defence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, to neglect them, account them as nothing, and deſpiſe them, without imputing them to thy ſelf, or charging thy Conſcience therewith. For thou wilt find this a ſure way, to put
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:152164:31"/>the Enemy to flight, if thou treat him, and his endeavours with the greateſt ſcorn and contempt; for he is exceeding proud, and cannot endure to be deſpis'd, and ſet at naught. Wherefore be ſure to make uſe of this, as the beſt and ſureſt Remedy againſt all ſuch injections, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to mind them, or be troubled at them, any more than thou art at flies, that buzz about thee againſt thy will. Wherefore let the Servant of Jeſus Chriſt take care not to run ſo eaſily from the face of the Lord, by being angry, murmuring and vexing himſelf about the buzzing of a ſilly Flie; I mean for ſome ſlight temptation, ſuſpicion, ſorrow, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction, weakneſs, or any other kind of Adverſity; ſeeing that by the hand only of Good Will lift up to God, all theſe, and a thouſand ſuch like, may be eaſily chaſed away, and put to flight. For by Good Will, Man has God to be his Poſſeſſor, and Owner, the Holy An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels his Guardians and Protectors; and moreover by the ſame, all Temptations are as eaſily overcome, as a Flie is cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed away with the leaſt motion of the hand. Peace therefore is the portion of
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:152164:31"/>the Men of Good Will; neither can any more worthy preſent be offer'd to God than it; for as much as Good Will in the Soul, is the Original of all good, and the Mother of all Virtues; which, whoſoever begins to be poſſeſſed of, he hath without care whatſoever is neceſſary to a good and happy Life; wherefore if thou willeſt that which is good, without, being able to perform it, God will make up from himſelf, what is wanting in thee, and accept the will for the deed; for an Eternal Law has unchangeably decreed and eſtabliſht that all Merit ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt and be in the Will alone, as reward, or puniſhment, are in happineſs, or mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery. For Love is a ſtrong will to ſerve God, a ſweet affection of pleaſing God, and a moſt burning deſire of enjoying God. Beſides, it is no Sin to be tempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but rather an occaſion of exerciſing ones Virtues; for certain it is, that we get much good by Temptation, ſeeing that our whole Life here upon Earth, is but one long continual Temptation.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="12" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="44" facs="tcp:152164:32"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. XII.</hi> Concerning the Love of God, and how Powerful it is.</head>
                     <p>NOW all theſe things above ſaid, and whatſoever elſe are neceſſary to Salvation, cannot be better, more readily, or more ſavingly performed than by Love; by which the want o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> every thing that is needful to Salvation is eaſily ſupplyed, and in it is the abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of all Good; neither does it wan the preſence of the moſt deſirable Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject. For it is Love alone whereby we are turn'd to God, transformed into God, cleave to God, and are united to him, to that degree, as to <hi>become on Spirit with him,</hi> and ſo are made hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py here in Grace, and hereafter in Glory, from him, in him, and by him For Love never reſts but in the beloved Object, when it is poſſeſt of the ſame with a full and peaceable poſſeſſion. Love or Charity is the way of God to Men, and of Men to God; and God cannot take up his Habitation any where, but
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:152164:32"/>where Charity is. If therefore we have Charity, we have God himſelf, <hi>for God is Love, or Charity.</hi> There is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more ſharp than Love, nothing more ſubtle, nothing more penetrating than Love; neither doth it ever reſt, until naturally it have penetrated the whole virtue, profundity, and totality of the amiable Object; it will make it ſelf one with its Beloved, and if poſſible, would be the the very ſame thing with it; and therefore it will not endure any thing to mediate or come between it, and the Object it loves, which is God, but doth with vehemence preſs into him, and never reſts 'till it have paſt by all things, and be come not only to him, but into him. For Love is an uniting and transforming Power or Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, transforming the Lover into the Beloved, and the Beloved into the Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver; ſo that one Lover is in the other, after the moſt intimate and preſential manner imaginable. Which is very ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent in the firſt place, with reference to the apprehenſive Powers, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Beloved is in the Lover; foraſmuch as the Beloved Object is always ſweetly
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:152164:33"/>and delightfully recall'd and repreſented in the apprehenſion of the Lover; and on the other hand, foraſmuch as the Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver endeavours, not ſuperficially, but intrinſically to diſcern and penetrate t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> the moſt inward parts of the beloved Object. And as to the appetitive and deſiring Powers, the Beloved in ſaid to be in the Lover, foraſmuch as it is moſt intimately rooted by an affectionate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placency, and pleaſurable delectation it him: And on-the other hand, the Love is in the Beloved, by means of a tota<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> deſire and conformity, as having but on willing, and nilling, one grief, and joy, as if they were indeed one and the ſame and no longer two diſtinct Beings.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Cam.</hi> 8.6.</note> For Love, <hi>which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> ſtrong as Death,</hi> draws th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Lover out of himſelf, and placeth him in the Beloved Object, making him to cloſe moſt intimately therewith. For the Soul is more truly where it loves, than where it moves, becauſe it is in the Beloved according to its own proper nature, reaſon, and will; but in that which it moves, or animates; it is only ſo far forth as it is a form, which is alſo
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:152164:33"/>competible to Beaſts. There is therefore nothing elſe that can draw us from all outward ſenſibles, and make us retire within our ſelves, and from thence into the heart, and inmoſt Divinity of Jeſus Chriſt, but the Love of Chriſt, and the longing deſire after the ſweetneſs of Chriſt, to feel, perceive, and to taſte the intimate preſence of Chriſt's Divinity. It is nothing elſe but the immenſe power of Love, which mounts a Man from the dregs of Earth, to the High Glory of Heaven. Neither is it poſſible for any one ever to attain the ſupream Bliſs and Beatitude, but with the help of Love, and Deſire. For Love is the true and genuine life of the Soul, the Wedding-Garment, and its utmoſt perfection, in which, all the Law,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>John</hi> 13.34. &amp; Ch. 15.7.</note> and the Prophets, yea, and <hi>our Lord's Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> too, are included, as being the Center and Subſtance of them all. And therefore St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells us, in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Romans, That Love is the fullfilling of the Law.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Rom. 13.10. 1 Tim. 1.5.</note> And in his firſt E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle to <hi>Timothy, That Charity is the end of the Cemmandment.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="13" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="48" facs="tcp:152164:34"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. XIII.</hi> The Qualifications of true Prayer, and the uſefulneſs thereof; and how the Heart is to be recollected, and gathered up into it ſelf.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>AND foraſmuch as we of our ſelves are altogether inſufficient for theſe, and all other good things; and that we cannot of our ſelves render any thing to our Lord God (from whom alone pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds all good) which was not his own before, ſave one thing only; according to what he himſelf, with his Bleſſed Mouth and Example hath been pleas'd to inſtruct us,</hi> viz. <hi>That we in all Caſes and Events have continual re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to Prayer (as being Guilty, Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable, Poor, Beggars, Weak, Deſtitute, Subjects, Servants, and Sons, and wholly deſolate in our ſelves) and that we, with the moſt humble proſtration of our mind, in Fear and Love, recollectedly, and compoſedly; with a deliberate true naked affection of ſhame, with earneſt deſire and fervency, with inward groans
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:152164:34"/>of the Heart, and with ſimplicity and ſincerity of Mind ſhould ſupplicate him, and lay open before him with full Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence, all our impending dangers; and readily, ſecurely and nakedly commit, reſign, and offer up our ſelves totally and faithfully to him, to our very laſt breath, as being truly and entirely his, reſerving nothing to our ſelves; that ſo the ſaying of the Bleſſed Father</hi> Iſaak <hi>may be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled in us,<note place="margin">In Caſſian. col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lat. <hi>10.</hi> c. <hi>6.</hi>
                           </note> who ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this king of Prayer, ſaith,</hi> Then it is that we ſhall be one in God, and our Lord God alone ſhall be all in all in us, when that perfect Love, wherewith he hath firſt loved us, ſhall become the Love and Affection of our our Love, all our deſire, all our ſtudy, and our endeavour, and laſtly all our Thoughts; yea, and every thing that we ſee, ſpeak, or hope for, ſhall be God; and when that Unity which now is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Father and the Son, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Son and the Father, ſhall be transfus'd into our Sence and Mind; to that degree, That as he Loves us
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:152164:35"/>with a ſincere, pure, and unchangeable Love; So we alſo may be joyned to him, by a perpetual and inſeparable dilection; being ſo intimately united to him, that whatſoever we hope, whatſoever we un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, whatſoever we ſpeak and pray for, may be God. This therefore muſt be the Purpoſe, this the endeavour and end of a truly Spiritual Man, to be found worthy to poſſeſs the Image of the future Beatitude in this Corruptible Body, and to obtain a foretaſte of that Celeſtial Bliſs, Converſation and Glory even in this Tranſitory Life. This is the end of all Perfection, that the Mind being purified from all the Dregs of Carnality, may be ſublimed to that pitch of Spirituality, That its whole Converſation, and all the outgoings of the Heart, be nothing elſe but one continual never ceaſing Prayer. And when the Mind thus, having ſhak'd off its Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Defilements and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanglements,<note place="margin">Collat. <hi>9.</hi> c. <hi>5.</hi>
                        </note> doth breath out it ſelf to God, in whom alone the intention of a Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Man ought always to be fixed (from which Soveraign Good, the leaſt Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration ought to be look'd upon as preſent
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:152164:35"/>Death, and the moſt pernicious Deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction) and that ſhe (the Mind) being well founded and rooted in foregoing Peace and Tranquility, and ſet looſe from the Bands of all Carnal Paſſions, and by a moſt reſolute and tenacious purpoſe cleaves to that one Soveraign Good, then I ſay ſhe will be able to fulfil that Command of the Apoſtle,<note place="margin">1 Theſ. 5.17.</note> Pray without ceaſing, and in all place,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 2.8.</note> lifting up Holy Hands without Wrath and doubting. For the Sence of the Mind being as it were wholly ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorpt by this Purity, and Transformed from its Earthly State into a Spiritual or Angelical likeneſs, in this condition what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ſhe takes in, whatſoever ſhe han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles, whatſoever ſhe does, will be the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt and trueſt Prayer. <hi>Wherefore if thou ſhalt without interruption continue this Exerciſe, as has been here ſet down from the beginning, it will be as eaſie and obvious to thee, in thy introverſion and Recollection, to contemplate and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy, as it is for thee to live in Nature.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="14" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:152164:36"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. XIV.</hi> In all Judgments that are made of us, we are ſtill to have Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to the Teſtimony of our Conſcience.</head>
                     <p>MOreover to attain to this Spiritual Perfection, Purity and Tranquil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of Mind in God, it will be of no ſmall Advantage to us, that, in all things which may be ſpoke or judged of us, or acted towards us, we always ſilently betake our ſelves, to the inmoſt retreat of our Minds, and there being abſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted from all other things, and totally recollected within our ſelves, place our ſelves before the Tribunal of Truth within us, where we ſhall plainly find and ſee, that it is not only of no Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, but a great hinderance to us, to be Praiſed and Honoured from without, when according to the knowledge of Truth in our ſelves we are indeed cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable and guilty. And as in this Caſe it is of no Advantage at all to a Man
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:152164:36"/>to be Praiſed outwardly by Men, when his Conſcience accuſeth him within; ſo neither on the contrary is it any the leaſt hurt or hinderance to a Man, if he be deſpiſed, reviled, blamed and perſecuted from without, when he is inwardly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent, unreproveable and harmleſs: Yea rather he hath great Reaſon in Patience, ſilence, and Peace, to rejoyce in the Lord on this account, foraſmuch as no adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity can hurt, where iniquity doth not prevail. And as no Wickedneſs ever goes unpuniſhed, ſo no good can be without its reward: Neither let us be willing with Hypocrites to expect or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive our Reward or Recompence from Men, but of our Lord God alone; not at preſent, but hereafter; not in this Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitory time, but in Eternity. It is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent therefore that there is nothing of greater Moment, or better for us, than alway in every Tribulation and Event to retire to the inmoſt ſecret of our Minds, and there to call upon the Lord Jeſus Chriſt himſelf, who is our helper in Temptations and Tribulations, and there to be humbled before him, Confeſſing our Sins, and to Praiſe God and our Father,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:152164:37"/>who as he bruiſes and chaſtens, ſo he alſo Comforts and Heals us: And over and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>bove all this to take and accept of all and every thing readily and ſecurely happening to our ſelves or others, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Proſperous or Adverſe, with an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven quiet Temper of Mind, from the Hand of his unerring Providence, and orderly diſpoſing of all Things: from the faithful diſcharge of which Exerciſe and Duty will follow the Remiſſion of our Sins, the Expulſion of all Bitterneſs, the Collation of Sweetneſs, Peace, and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity, the infuſion of Grace and Mercy, the attraction and ſtrengthening of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarity and Communion, with moſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundant Comfort in him, and firm cleaving to, and Union with him. But by no means let us be willing to imitate thoſe, who through Hypocriſie, and Phariſaical Pride, make it their Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to be ſeen, eſteemed, and to appear more Holy outwardly before Men, than the Truth within them bears Witneſs to, which certainly is a piece of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremeſt Folly and Madneſs, to deſire and long for Humane Praiſe and Glory from ones ſelf, or others, when at the ſame
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:152164:37"/>time we are inwardly full of the flicker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing inticements of this World, and moſt Grievous Sins. And certainly whoever purſues theſe moſt vain things, the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Goods will fly from him, and he will fall into Shame and Diſgrace: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore have thou always before thine Eyes thy manifold Sins and Wickedneſs, and thy unfitneſs for any thing that is good, and endeavour to know thy ſelf, that thou mayſt be Humbled; and don't refuſe, or be afraid to be eſteemed and judged by all, as the vileſt unworthieſt, and moſt abject Off-ſcouring and Filth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of thy moſt Grievous Sins, and great Iniquities. Do thou therefore re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute thy ſelf amongſt others, as Droſs amongſt Gold, as Tares amongſt Wheat, as Chaff amongſt Corn, as a Wolf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Sheep, and as Satan amongſt the Sons of God. Neither do thou in the leaſt deſire to be Reverenc'd or Honour'd by Men, or to be preferr'd before o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; but rather with thy whole Heart and Spirit flee from the Infections of this Peſtilence, the Poyſon of Praiſe, and the Pride of Boaſting and Oſtentation;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10.3.</note> leſt the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:152164:38"/>
                        <hi>Wicked ſhould be Praiſed in the deſire of his Heart,</hi> and ſo be in the condition of thoſe of whom the Prophet faith;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Iſa.</hi> 3.12.</note> 
                        <hi>O my People! they which call thee Bleſſed, cauſe thee to erre, and overturn the way of thy going;</hi> or fall under that Curſe of our Lord:<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Luke</hi> 6.26.</note> 
                        <hi>Wo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you when all Men ſhall ſpeak well of you; for ſo did their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>there to the falſe Prophets.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="15" type="chapter">
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. XV.</hi> How we may arrive to a thorough Contempt of our ſelves, and how profitable it is.</head>
                     <p>THE more therefore that any Man knows his own Vileneſs, the more diſtinct and clear is his View and Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Divine Majeſty; and the more Baſe and Vile any one appears in his own Eyes, for God, Truth and Righteouſneſs, the more Precious he is
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:152164:38"/>in the Eyes of God. Wherefore let us ſtrive, with the total Effort of our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, to think our ſelves the Vileſt of all Men, and to believe our ſelves unworthy of every Benefit; to diſpleaſe our ſelves, and to pleaſe God alone, and be willing to be judged by others the moſt inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable and deſpicable Creatures. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over let us endeavour not to be moved by any Tribulations, Afflictions or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries; nor to be troubled at thoſe that bring them upon us, nor to entertain a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hard Thoughts, or to have indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt them, but with an even and quiet Mind to believe that we do well deſerve all Injuries, ſlightings, Chaſtiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Derelictions. For certainly he who truly Mourns and is Penitent ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to God, he abhorrs to be Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour'd or Belov'd by others; and doth not avoid or refuſe to be hated, trod up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and wholly deſpis'd; to the end that he may be truly humbled, and with a Pure Heart may ſincerely cleave to his Lord God alone. Now that we may ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive to this Loving of the Lord God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, and the abhorring of our ſelves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all Things, and to the deſire of
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:152164:39"/>being deſpis'd by othess, there is not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired any outward Labour, or Health and Strength of Body, but rather ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of Body, Labour of the Heart and Quiet of the Mind; That by Labour of the Heart, and Affection of the inmoſt Mind we may raiſe our ſelves above, and Bodily withdraw our ſelves from theſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferious Things, and ſo riſe and mount up to thoſe that are Heavenly and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine. For doing this, we change our ſelves into God: And this is then chiefly done, when we chooſe from our Hearts, without any judging, Condemning or Contemning of our Neighbour, to be eſteem'd by all Men as meer Off-ſcouring, Filth, and Reproach, yea to be abhorred and trampled upon by all, as the Dirt in the Streets, rather than to abound in Pleaſures and Deliciouſneſs, or to be Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured and lifted up by Men; or to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy any Corporal and Tranſitory Health or Advantages; Or to deſire any other Comfort in this preſent Mortality and Bodily Life, but to Mourn, Lament and bewail, our Offences, Faults and Sins, without ceaſing, perfectly to ſet at naught and Annihilate our ſelves, and to be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:152164:39"/>daily ſtill Viler and Viler by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and appear daily more unworthy in our own Eyes, That we may pleaſe God alone, Love him only, and cleave unto him: Being unwilling to be Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with any thing, ſave only with our Lord Jeſus Chriſt himſelf; not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſollicitous or careful about any thing but him, under whoſe Rule and Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence all things ſubſiſt and have their Courſe. Know then, that henceforward it is not for thee to delight thy ſelf, but to Mourn with thy whole Heart; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if ſo be thou doſt not yet Mourn, Mourn for that; and if thou doſt Mourn, Mourn and Lament the more, for that thou haſt brought upon thy ſelf this Cauſe of Grief and Sorrow, becauſe of thy moſt Griveous Offences and Infinite Sins. For as a Malefactor who receives his Sentence of Death is not concern'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the ranging of the Sherifs Men, or the Multitude of the Spectators; So he who in good earneſt Mourns and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wails his Sins, cannot give his Mind to Pleaſures, or Anger, or vain Glory, or Indignation, or any other ſuch like. And as the Habitations of Citizens and
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:152164:40"/>Condemned Malefactors are very diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent; So the State, Manner, and Beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour of thoſe that Mourn, for being Guilty of Sins, that bind them over and make them obnoxious to Puniſhment, ought to be very different from thoſe who are Innocent and not Guilty: For otherwiſe there would be no difference made between a Guilty and Innocent Perſon by reward and Puniſhment; and Unrighteouſneſs would be more free, than Innocence. So that all things are to be denied, all things are to be Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned, all things are to be caſt away and avoided, That with full Faith, a good and ſure Foundation may be laid for the Sorrow of Repentance. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he that Loves Jeſus Chriſt in Truth, and that Mourns after him, and that bears him in his Heart, and in his Body, that truly Mourns for his Sins and Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, and earneſtly ſeeks for the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to come, and in true Faith poſſeſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Memory of the Torments of Hell and of Eternal Judgement, and imprinteth firmly and perfectly in his Heart the Senſe and Fear of his own Death, ſuch a one will no farther ſtrive,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:152164:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>care, or be ſollicitous about any other thing whatſoever. Let him therefore who haſtens to attain that Bleſſed im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſibility, and to approach to God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, account that every day wherein he is not reproach'd, revil'd, or contemn'd, he ſuffers great loſs and damage. Now this impaſſibility here mention'd, is nothing elſe, but a freedom from Vices and Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, Purity of Heart, and the entire Ornament of Vertues and Graces. Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe thy ſelf therefore already Dead, whom thou doubteſt not but muſt Dye certainly. And let this be the laſt and higheſt proof, and ſureſt Tryal of all thy Thoughts, Words and Actions, to prove whether they be according to God or no, if by them thou becomeſt more humble, and more recollected and fixed within thy ſelf and in God; but if thou findeſt the effect otherwiſe, thou wilt have good reaſon to ſuſpect, that they were not according to God, and neither well pleaſing to him, nor pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable for thee.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="16" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="62" facs="tcp:152164:41"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. XVI.</hi> How the Providence of God ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends it ſelf to all and every thing.</head>
                     <p>NOW to the end that according to the foregoing inſtructions, we may without let or hinderance, readily, ſecurely, and nakedly be carried towards the Lord our God, with the greateſt freedom and Tranquility become joyned with him and united to him, and may firmly cleave unto him, with an even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Temper whether in Proſperity, or Adverſity, Life or Death; it is of abſolute Neceſſity that we reſign and commit all and every thing, without the leaſt doubt, or heſitation, and with the greateſt aſſurance, to his unſearchable and infallible Providence. Neither ought we to think ſtrange of this Counſel, foras<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as it is he alone, that gives to all things their being, Power, and Activity, that is, their Subſtance, Vertue, Opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Kind, Manner and Order, and
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:152164:41"/>that in Number, Weight and Meaſure. And this, the rather becauſe as all Artiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Works, preſuppoſe the Works of Nature, ſo every Work of Nature, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuppoſeth the Work of God, Creating, Preſerving, Ordering and Adminiſtring: Since to him alone belongs Infinite Power, Wiſdom, Goodneſs, and Eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Mercy, Juſtice, Truth and Charity, immutable Eternity and Immenſity. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is evident, that nothing doth or on ſubſiſt by its own Virtue, nor Act, ſave only in the Virtue of God himſelf, that is of the firſt Mover and firſt Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, who is the Cauſe of all Actions, and Operates in every Agent. For with reſpect to the true Order of the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of the World, Go immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately provides and takes care for all Things, even to the utmoſt Individuals: So that nothing from the higheſt to the loweſt can eſcape or avoid the Eternal Providence of God, whether in things Natural or Voluntary, or Caſual and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuitous, which were never intended by the particular Agent. Neither can God make any thing, but what muſt of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity reſort or fall under the order of
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:152164:42"/>his Providence, no more than he can make any thing, which is not ſubject to his operating Power. It follows therefore that the Divine Providence doth extend it ſelf to all and every thing, even to the very Thoughts of Mens Hearts Upon which Foundation the Scripture builds the following Inſtructions. <hi>Caſting all your care upon him,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.7.</note> for he careth for you. Caſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> thy Burden upon the Lord, and he ſhall ſuſtain thee.<note place="margin">
                              <hi>Pſal.</hi> 55.22.</note> Look at the Generations of Old and ſee,<note place="margin">
                              <hi>Eccl. Syr.</hi> 2.10.</note> did ever any truſt in the Lord, and wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> forſaken? Or did ever any abide in his Fear, and was confounded?</hi> And that of our Saviour? <hi>Take no though for your Life,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.25.</note> 
                        <hi>wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> you ſhall eat, &amp;c.</hi> Wherefore let us aſſure our ſelves, that whatſoever, or how great ſoever the things are that we hope or expect from God; we ſhall without doubt receive the ſame, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to that Promiſe in <hi>Deuteronomy.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Deut.</hi> 11.24.</note> 
                        <hi>Every place whereon the Soles of your feet ſhall tread,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Joſh.</hi> 1.3.</note> 
                        <hi>ſhall be
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:152164:42"/>yours.</hi> Becauſe as much as every one can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, ſo much ſhall he receive; and as far as he can reach with the foot of his truſt and confidence, ſo far ſhall he poſſeſs. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly <hi>Bernard</hi> tells us: <hi>God the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of all things doth abound with ſuch Bowels of Love and Mercy, that to how great a degree ſoever of Grace, we can extend the reach of our truſt and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, the ſame we ſhall undoubtedly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive and be poſſeſt of:</hi> To which purpoſe our Saviour <hi>Mar.</hi> 11.24. alſo aſſures us: <hi>What things ſoever ye deſire when ye pray, believe that you receive them, and ye ſhall have them.</hi> Now the ſtronger and more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant this truſt and reliance in God is; And by how much the more forceably it lifts it ſelf up to, and preſſeth into God, with Humility and Reverence, the more aſſuredly, abundantly, and ſwift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it will obtain the deſired good. But and if it ſhould happen, that by reaſon of the Multitude or Greatneſs of Sin, the Affiance ſhould be luke-warm and ſlow in lifting up it ſelf to God, let ſuch a one conſider, that all things are poſſible with God; and that whatſoever he will muſt
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:152164:43"/>neceſſarily come to paſs: And that what he wills not, is for that very reaſon im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible; and it is as eaſie for him to forgive and blot out innumerable Sins, how enormous ſoever they may be, as one only Sin. And that as a Sinner can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not by all the Power that is in him, raiſe himſelf up again from his innumerable Sins, ſhake them off, and free himſelf from them, ſo neither from one only.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.5.</note> 
                        <hi>For we are not ſufficient of our ſelves to think any thing that is good,</hi> (much leſs to do it) <hi>but our Sufficiency is from God.</hi> Tho' in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed it be much more dangerous to be intangled with many Sins (all other Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances being alike) than with one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, becauſe there is no Evil with without its Puniſhment, and an Infinite Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is due to every mortal Sin; and this according to the Rigor of Juſtice, becauſe every ſuch Sin is committed againſt God who is of Infinite Reverence, Dignity and Honour. Moreover we are to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider that, according to the Apoſtle, the Lord knows thoſe that are his; and that it is impoſſible for any of thoſe to Periſh, in whatſoever windings and Floods of
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:152164:43"/>Errours, Scandals, Schiſms, Perſecutions, Diſſentions, Hereſies, Tribulations, Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities and Temptations they may be involved, ſeeing that the number of his Elect, and the bound of their Merits hath been eternally and unchangeably foreſeen by him; ſo that all things whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Good or Evil; proper, or ſtrange and Forreign; proſperous or adverſe, do all work together for their good, ſave only that they appear yet more Glorious and acceptable to God in Adverſity than Proſperity. Let us therefore ſecurely and readily commit all and every of our and others concerns with a plenary Truſt and Confidence to the Divine Providence, who therefore permits all manner of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils, in what way ſoever, to be done; and it is good and well done of him, that he ſuffers them to be done; neither can they be more or otherwiſe done, than as he permits them to be, becauſe he knows, can, and will change and diſpoſe them to ſomething that is better. For as all good things are done by his Operation, ſo by his Permiſſion all Evil things are made good. And by this means are manifeſted his Power, Wiſdom, and Clemency,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:152164:44"/>through our Saviour Chriſt, his Mercy and Juſtice, the Virtue and Strength of his Grace, and the weakneſs and failure of Nature, the Beauty of the Univerſe, which ſprings from the contrapoſition of oppoſites, the Praiſe of the Good, and the Wickedneſs and Puniſhment of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probates. So likewiſe in a Sinner con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted are manifeſted Contrition, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, and Repentance, as well as the Meekneſs and long Suffering of God, his Kindneſs and Charity, his Praiſe and Goodneſs. Not that it always tends to their Good, that do Wickedly, for moſt commonly indeed It doth precipitate them into great Danger, and the worſt of Evils, <hi>viz.</hi> the loſs of Grace and Glory, and obnoxiouſneſs to Guilt and Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ſometimes of that which is Eternal, from which the Lord Jeſus Chriſt of his Mercy preſerve us. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <group>
            <text xml:lang="eng">
               <front>
                  <div type="title_page">
                     <pb facs="tcp:152164:44"/>
                     <p>Two ancient Spiritual Treatiſes: OF Dr. <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Staupitz,</hi> Abbot of St. <hi>Peters</hi> at <hi>Saltsburg</hi> in <hi>Germany.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>CONCERNING <hi>The Sweet Love of God,</hi> And our Holy Chriſtian Faith.</p>
                     <p>Faithfully Tranſlated out of High-Dutch into Engliſh.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>R. Baldwin,</hi> near the <hi>Oxford-Arms-Inn</hi> in <hi>Warwick-Lane.</hi> 1692.</p>
                  </div>
               </front>
               <body>
                  <div n="1" type="chapter">
                     <pb facs="tcp:152164:45"/>
                     <pb n="71" facs="tcp:152164:45"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> God is Lovely above all Things.</head>
                     <p>IF any one enquire, how it can be made out that God is Lovely above all Things? He may anſwer himſelf, by conſidering that God is God, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently not only full of all Perfections, but Perfection it ſelf, in whom, by whom, and from whom all Perfection conſiſts, flows, and proceeds. As likewiſe that he is Love it ſelf, than which nothing can be found, or imagin'd, more Lovely, as being that very Love, which makes all things Lovely it lights upon; if it lights on an hateful Enemy, it changeth him into a Lovely Friend; if it lights on horrid Darkneſs, it becomes immediately changed into pleaſant Light; if it falls upon nothing, the nothing immediately is made ſomething, and ſomething that is good too. For it is impoſſible but that all whatſoever God Loves, muſt needs be Lovely. And every one eaſily
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:152164:46"/>conceives that without or beſides this Love nothing is or can be Lovely, and that nothing that is unlovely can flow from it, becauſe it is the ſelf-ſubſiſting eſſential Love, whoſe goodneſs is in and of it ſelf. Our Love receives the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure or proportion of its goodneſs from the goodneſs of the beloved Object, and is then only good when it Loves ſome thing that is good, and better when it Loves ſomething that is better, and beſt of all, when it Loves the higheſt good; and on the other hand becomes evil, when it Loves that which is not good. Nay whatſoever Object it lights upon, whether Good or Evil, yet to Love is always ſweet and lovely in it ſelf. Wherefore alſo, it makes all things not only tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, but eaſie and delightful, which without it would be difficult to endure if not altogether intollerable. How then is it poſſible that the higheſt, beſt, unal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terable, conſtant Faithfulneſs, and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Love, which is God himſelf, ſhould be loveleſs, harſh, or unpleaſant?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="73" facs="tcp:152164:46"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> God muſt be Loved above all things.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>THou ſhalt Love the Lord thy God</hi> (ſaith <hi>Moſes</hi> and our Lord Jeſus Chriſt) <hi>with all thy heart, with all thy Soul,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Matth.</hi> 22.37. <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.5.</note> 
                        <hi>with all thy Mind, and with all Strength</hi> above things. This is what all of us are bound to do, by Vertue of his Command, and the Obedience we we owe him, and this becauſe he is our God, to whom out of Love we are to return, and give up again all that we are, and all that we have, our Heart, Soul, Mind, Strength and Power, Houſe ad Goods, Lands and Poſſeſſions, Wife and Children, Brothers and Siſters, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Mother, and in a word nothing excepted, even our ſelves alſo, to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed of, as he pleaſes, for Death or for Life, for Heaven or for Hell; Theſe are indeed very hard works, which not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding a ſuperlative lovely Love is able to make Light, ſweet and eaſy: Foraſmuch then, as God will have all
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:152164:47"/>this Performed by us, and will not accept of it, as it proceeds from a ſorrowful, but chearful Mind, therefore it is that he worketh in us his Love above all things, that we may be able to perform his will herein.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="chapter">
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Where God is not loved above all Things, there he is not Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied as God.</head>
                     <p>ALL Men are Created to this end, That they might praiſe and honor God, and magnifie and glorifie him in themſelves with Hearts, Words and Works. Now there is no other way, whereby the Heart and Will may give to God his peculiar and higheſt Honour, than by reſting in his Love, and by loving him only for himſelf, with all the Heart, Soul and Mind, being altogether ſatia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and ſatisfied with his Divine Perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and wholly emptied of all other Love beſide. For whoſoever loves God for his own advantage, or any thing that is Outward or Temporal, he prefers the Creature before the Creator, and
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:152164:47"/>Robs God of his Glory, and higheſt Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and makes that to be his God, which is not God. For that which the Heart loves moſt, the ſame it Honours as God, whatſoever the Mouth may ſay to the contrary. Who knows not, that if a Chriſtian ſhould now a days ſay, that his Wife was his God, or his Children, or his Goods, he would be condemn'd for a Blaſphemer, if he perſiſted therein; and yet who is there of us, who doth not ſee in the daily practice and Actions of Men, that Temporal Goods, Pleaſure and Honour are preferred before God and his Love, to that degree, that it is matter of juſt Lamentation? We will by no means endure the reproach of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Idolaters, tho indeed we are ſo real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and in Truth, no leſs than others were of Old. At this very day, O gracious God! Many in Chriſtendome, Worſhip Cows, Horſes, Gold, Silver, Wood, and the Goods of this World, as the Heathens did thouſand years ago, notwithſtanding they ſay with their Mouths, <hi>Our Father which art in Heaven,</hi> for true Adoration conſiſts in Loving, and not in Speaking. He prays well,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:152164:48"/>who loves much, and he who loves not, neither does, nor can pray, tho he ſhould repeat a thouſand Pſalms or Prayers. He who loves God, ſerves him; but he who doth not love him, neither doth, nor can ſerve him, how great Works ſoever he may outwardly perform. Wherefore nothing can be more uſeful and advantageous to Men, than to excite, draw and perſwade them to the love of God, eſpecially in this miſerable ſtate we are in, where we are oft hindred from lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving by want of neceſſaries, which we cannot be without, by outward profit, which we can hardly deny our ſelves in, and by our inborn infirmity, which no body of himſelf can rid himſelf of, to which we may likewiſe add, the Pomp, Luxury, and Vanity of this World, and the Cunning, Malice and Tyranny of our grand Enemy the Devil.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="chapter">
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> To love God above all things cannot be learned of Men.</head>
                     <p>NO Man can teach another the things, that can no other ways be known, but by Senſe and Experience, no Man can
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:152164:48"/>teach another to ſee, hear, ſmell, taſte, feel or experience, and much leſs to love, rejoyce, to be ſorrowful, and ſuch like, which muſt be felt and experienced before they can be known. We muſt taſte it in our ſelves, and God muſt work it in us. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>David</hi> ſaith, <hi>Taſte and ſee that the Lord is Good,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pſ.</hi> 34.8.</note> ſweet or gracious. We may indeed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form others of the viſibility of colors, and of the qualifications that are required in the eye to perceive its proper Objects, but by all our diligence we can never teach others to ſee: ſo we may diſcourſe much and at large concerning the perfect and ſupreme Goodneſs of God, and the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtation of his Love, which alſo is very good and commendable; In like manner we may diſcourſe of the property of the will, of purity of heart, of a good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience and Faith unfeigned, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 1.5.</note> 
                        <hi>The end of the command is Love, out of a pure heart, a good Conſcience and Faith unfeigned.</hi> But we can never teach another how to love, and much leſs to love above all things; for this is a work of God, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved to him, as his peculiar Royalty,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:152164:49"/>who has <hi>the heart in his hand,</hi> and the will in his power,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pro.</hi> 21.1.</note> to turn, and <hi>incline them, how and which way it pleaſeth him.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="chapter">
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> To Love God above all things, a Man cannot learn of himſelf.</head>
                     <p>IT is true, that the natural Underſtanding of Man, may from the knowledg of the Creatures, raiſe it ſelf to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of God, and of <hi>his eternal Power and Godhead; Rom.</hi> 1.20. and accordingly the Philoſopher tells us, that there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing better than God; but foraſmuch as they only continue in the ſpeculation hereof, without feeling and experiencing the Love and Goodneſs of God opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively in themſelves, which muſt be, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that knowledg can beget or kindle Divine Love; wherefore neither do they know God aright. Accordingly St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells us. (<hi>Rom.</hi> 1.21.) That <hi>tho they knew God, they glorifyed him not as God, neither were thankful:</hi> wherefore alſo this their knowledg turns to their greater hurt and prejudice, particularly in that in renders
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:152164:49"/>them <hi>inexcuſable,</hi> making them to become vain in their imagination, and darkning their fooliſh hearts to that degree, that they beſtow the honour, which is due to him alone, <hi>viz. Love above all things</hi> upon the Creature; wherefore alſo God ſuffers them to fall into Sin and Shame, and to defile themſelves with unnatural Luſts, that they may receive in themſelves the recompence due to their Error; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they do not like or value the true knowledg of God, God gives them o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to a reprobate mind, ſo as to fall from one Sin into another, and do thoſe things which are not convenient. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore certainly it is much better for a Man never to know God, than not to glorifie the known God, as God, or not to love him above all things.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="chapter">
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> To Love God above all things can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be learnt from the Letter of the Scripture.</head>
                     <p>IN the Old Teſtament we are taught the written Law of God, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in alſo we find wiſe Inſtructions, how the
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:152164:50"/>ſaid Law muſt be kept or obſerved. As likewiſe the good and advantage which accrues to Men by keeping of the ſame, as well as the loſs and evil that happens to Men for tranſgreſſing of it. But when we come to compare our duty with our performance, then it appears that we ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver kept any one of the Divine Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, and that we are throughout de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed with Sin. We know alſo that no Man can keep the Law, except he love God above all things, and that the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Scripture can never teach us this; for if the Love of God above all things did grow out of the Letter of the Old Law, then it would follow, that none did love God more than the Jews, who abound in the knowledg of the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Law. But the Apoſtle tells us, that the Law never brought any one to <hi>Perfection,</hi> that is to the <hi>Love of God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all things,</hi> which is the <hi>higheſt perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Man;</hi> for the Letter of the Old Law brings forth nothing but the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of our Duty, that we ought to keep the Commandments of God; the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of our Sin, that we have tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them; the knowledg of our weakneſs
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:152164:50"/>and inability, that we are not able to keep them; and knowledg of the eternal pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, we muſt ſuffer for it, whence fear and bondage is engendred, and more than this the Letter cannot do; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore alſo the Letter kills, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells us, but cannot-quicken, it diſcovers our ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but cannot recover us to health; it manifeſts Sin, and declares the greatneſs of our Fall, but cannot raiſe us up again, yet there is this comfort in it, for that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this Letter the Spirit lyes hid, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Old Law is big with child of Chriſt, through whom the Grace of Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God above all things is conferred. They who have found this Spirit, and who know and acknowledg Chriſt to be hid in the Law, to thoſe, I ſay, the Scripture is a profitable Doctrine, and, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>full of comfort,</hi> and particularly in this, that ſuch as theſe, as they find their Sickneſs in the Scriptures, ſo likewiſe their Strength and Health; as they find the Death of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſo likewiſe the quickening of Grace through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord, in whom alſo they love God above all things, and are able perfectly to fulfil and perform the Law. From all which we ſee that the
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:152164:51"/>Law is only an Affrightment or Terror driving us from Nature to Grace, from our ſelves into God, from Fleſh into the Spirit, in and by whom we cry to God, <hi>Abba Father,</hi> and come to deſire or long for God above all things. In like manner alſo is the Letter of the New Teſtament a Murtherer of Souls, more than the Letter of the Old Law, becauſe it repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents God more lovely than that doth, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven as our Redeemer, and who for our ſakes was made Man, ſuffered, was cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, dead and buried, upon all which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts we cannot but acknowledg our ſelves in the higheſt degree bound to love him above all things. Now it is evident that we make our ſelves lyable to greater Sins and Damnation, when after ſo unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſible great mercy and benefits receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, we continue unthankful and go on in our Sins. Theſe and ſuch like are the effects of the Letter of the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and therefore it kills as well as that of the Law. For tho it repreſents Chriſt to the Eye, and his Doctrine to the Ear, yet foraſmuch as it is unable to bring the Spirit of Chriſt into the heart, it ſerves only to work a more grievous Death. The
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:152164:51"/>Jews had Chriſt before their Eyes, in their Ears, and in their Hands, but they had not the Spirit of Chriſt in their Hearts, and therefore were in a more damnable condition than the Heathens. They had received many more benefits from him than from any one beſides, but yet did not love him in the higheſt degree, who had loved them to the utmoſt, ſo as to give his Life for them. And thus at this day we frequently find, that thoſe who have Chriſt moſt in their Tongues, have him leaſt in their Hearts, whence follows, that they alſo communicate or impart him to others, ſo as they have him themſelves, <hi>viz.</hi> on the Tongue and not in the Heart, they teach them to talk much of him, but to love little, by which means the poor ſimple People are much hindred in the way to true Perfection and happineſs.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="84" facs="tcp:152164:52"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> The Love of God above all things, cannot enter into a Man, except the Holy Ghoſt be there before.</head>
                     <p>SAint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>The Love of God is ſhed abroad in our hearts through the Holy Ghoſt, which is given unto us,</hi> even the Spirit of our heavenly Father, the Spirit of Chriſt, whom he that hath not, is none of Chriſts, neither is it poſſible for ſuch an one to love God above all things. Wherefore we are to take notice, that the firſt, the greateſt, and the higheſt Favor God beſtows upon a choſen Soul, is, that he vouchſafes to take up his Dwelling in him. By this means it is, that the eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Self ſubſiſting Love, which is God himſelf, is always in Man before his own Love, or any thing that can be called Good, and much the ſame thing happens to every pious Soul, as befel the bleſſed Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> the Mother of God, when it was told her by the Angel, That ſhe ſhould conceive, and be with child of God; whereupon when the Virgin de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, how this ſhould come to paſs, and
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:152164:52"/>by whom, ſeeing it was not to be accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Order of Nature? To which queſtion ſhe (and all holy Souls with her) received this Anſwer <hi>The Holy Ghoſt ſhall come upon thee, and the Power of the Higheſt ſhall over-ſhadow thee,</hi> Luk. 1.35. As if he had ſaid, a Child of God is <hi>not born of Blood, nor of the Luſt of the Fleſh, nor of the Will of Man, but is born of God alone, Job.</hi> 1.13. In which Birth the Soul is endued with Divine Power, to fulfil all things, and all Commands through the Love of God. Wherefore if at any time any thing that is holy or good be done by us, we muſt not attribute and appropriate it to our ſelves, but to God only, who is the only Father of all good Fruits and Gifts in us. Upon which Account alſo, the Angel gives us this further Information, ſaying, <hi>there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that holy thing which ſhall be born of thee ſhall be called the Son of God.</hi> O happy, yea more than happy is that Man, into whom the Holy Ghoſt is come down from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove, in whom the ſelf-ſubſiſting eſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Love, which is God himſelf, hath taken up his abode, for in him continually and for ever Divine Fruits grow and ſpring forth, whether he knows it or not; for
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:152164:53" rendition="simple:additions"/>the Holy Ghoſt is never idle. Sometimes he ſtirs in us motions of Anger, to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend and reprove that which he will have reproved; ſometimes he moves us to mirth, and jocoſe words to revive and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce thoſe whom he will have comforted, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and frequently makes us in thoſe ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry things his Fruits and Children, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we are apt to fear, that we were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come his Enemies. Many, very many Fruits of our Salvation doth he work in us, whereof we know nothing neither more nor leſs. Could we now in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner always ſee him in our ſelves, and clearly diſcern and know him, this would be to be happy indeed here on Earth; but it hath rather pleaſed him, and ſeemed good in his Eyes, to be hidden and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed in us, according to the Saying of the Prophet <hi>David, Pſ.</hi> 18.11. <hi>He bowed the Heavens and came down, and Darkneſs was under his Feet, he made Darkneſs his hiding Place, his covering round about him, were dark Waters,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="87" facs="tcp:152164:53"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> From the Indwelling of the Holy Ghoſt, firſt proceeds the Light of true Chriſtian Faith.</head>
                     <p>THat no Man can reach the Senſe and Power of the Holy Scriptures, or the Love of God above all things, from any outward Learning or Information what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, our Lord <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> himſelf plainly declares, when he ſaith to his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples, <hi>Job.</hi> 16.12. <hi>I have yet many things to ſay to you, but ye cannot bear them now. It is expedient for you that I go away; for if I go not away, the Holy Ghoſt will not come unto you; but if I depart I will ſend him to you: And when He, the Spirit of Truth is come, he will guide you into all Truth, and teach you all things, and will open to you the hidden, myſtical <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderstanding of the things I have ſpoke to you.</hi> Chriſt muſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part and paſs away from the Eyes into the Heart, from the Fleſh into the Spirit, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ever he can be known to Salvation. Upon which Account he himſelf diſowns the Fruit of his outward Doctrine, when the ſame is ſeparated and divided from
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:152164:54"/>the inward Teaching. It is in this ſenſe, St. <hi>Paul</hi> declares, that as well his Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as that of all the other Apoſtles, was nothing, except God himſelf teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in the Heart. Neither can any man with any words how high and choice ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they may be, declare, make out, or repreſent the above meaſure love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Love of God, if God do not firſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal himſelf in the Heart. Wherefore it is without all doubt, that God himſelf brings into the Soul of thoſe by whom he will be loved above all things, that Light, whereby his great Lovelineſs and Kindneſs are clearly ſeen and diſcerned, through a firm Faith, without doubting, before ever we know, or underſtand what is right and good. Wherefore we muſt conclude that the knowledge of the True Chriſtian Faith, is a pure meer Grace of God.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="89" facs="tcp:152164:54"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> That Man is never comforted in hope, whom the Spirit of God himſelf doth not comfort.</head>
                     <p>ALL the comfort of this World is Vain, Uſeleſs and Empty; all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence in the Creature is deceitful; for which reaſon the Holy Scriptures denounce Curſes againſt all thoſe who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fide in their own,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Jer.</hi> 17.5, 6.</note> or others created pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er or ability, and by this means ſeek their comfort in, and from the Creature. The only true comfort upon Earth is founded and grounded in this, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> aſſures us, that we <hi>boaſt our ſelves and Triumph in the Glory</hi> of the Children <hi>of God,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.2, 11.</note> that is in our indubitable aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, that we are the Children of God, foreknown and Elected to Eternal glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. This is the comfort which no Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture can give, neither can any deſerve it, it muſt and can only be given by the Holy Ghoſt, the Comforter, to whom only it belongs to comfort his People,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:152164:55"/>and whoſe property it is to convey a lively hope, into the heart of his choſen, and this even before there is any Merit in them. Neither hath our ſaving hope any other Source or Spring, ſave only the Benigne, Kind and Merciful Will of God, even that very ſelf ſubſiſting Eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Love which is God himſelf. Accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly our hope is not in any degree founded on the Love we have to God, nor on the Duties or Services we perform to God, or for his ſake, but is only grounded on the Love which <hi>God</hi> bears to us, and the Works, that he himſelf operates in us. This the Apoſtle St. <hi>Paul</hi> plainly and openly declares, from the High Spirit he had received of God, for after that he had ſpoke to the <hi>Romans,</hi> concerning the comfort of Hope, he im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately declares to them from whence the ſame proceeds, ſaying. <hi>And hope maketh not aſhamed becauſe the Love of God is ſhed abroad in our Hearts,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. <hi>v.</hi> 5.</note> 
                        <hi>through the Holy Ghoſt, which is given unto us.</hi> This is the ſaving Comfort and higheſt Conſolation of Man, that out of the inexpreſſible Love of <hi>God,</hi> the Holy <hi>Ghoſt</hi> is given
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:152164:55"/>unto him, though the Merit of Chriſt, not of his deſert, as it is written,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.8, 9, 10.</note> 
                        <hi>But God Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth his Love towards us, in that he died for us whileſt we were yet Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</hi> Foraſmuch then as he hath ſo high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly loved us, whilſt we were yet Sinners, as to reconcile us to his Heavenly Father, when we did not deſire in the leaſt any ſuch thing of him, how can it be then, that being now reconciled through him to the Father, we ſhould not be ſaved, yet not in our own, but in his Life? For moſt ſure it is, that all Life muſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from one Life, as all Deaths pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded at firſt from one Death. From all which it follows, that they are not our own works, that can give us comfort, ſo as that from them we ſhould be able to conceive a true and lively hope towards God, but they afford us only a comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table conjecture, that this true hope is in us; in the very ſame manner as each fruit points us to the tree upon which it grew. It is in this Senſe St. <hi>Peter</hi> tells, us,<note place="margin">2 Pet. 1.10.</note> that we muſt <hi>be diligent to make our Calling and Election to Eternal Salvation ſure</hi> by the
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:152164:56"/>good Works we do. When the Holy Ghoſt is in any Soul, her condition may be compared to water ſpringing out of a Rock. Now in this caſe firſt, there muſt be water in the Rock, for otherwiſe none could ever ſpring thence; in the next place, thoſe hidden ſpringing waters muſt make a Well, before that ever any ſtreams can proceed from them. Wherefore as the ſtreams or rivulets lead us to the Well or Spring, and the Spring to the hidden Water; in like manner do good Works lead us to the Fountain, wherein Faith, Hope and Love do firſt ſpring, and theſe three again, lead us to the inward hidden Water, even to the Holy Ghoſt, who is the ſelf-ſubſiſting Eſſential Love of <hi>God.</hi> By this very compariſon or Similitude <hi>God</hi> leads the <hi>Samaritan</hi> Woman from the Water ſhe drew out of <hi>Jacob</hi>'s Well, to that Water, which is <hi>God</hi> himſelf, which through Faith, Hope and Love becomes a Well ſpringing up into Eternal Life, and flowing forth in the ſtreams of all good Vertues and Graces. For the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> is the hidden Water, Faith, Hope and Love are the Spring that make the Well or Fountain, and good Works are
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:152164:56"/>the Streams or Rivulets. Thus you ſee for a concluſion, that no good Work can be in us, except the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> be there before, as hath been already menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned. Now when he dwells in us, then is he himſelf in us that Living Water, which becomes in us a Well ſpringing up into Eternal Life, through Faith, Hope and Love. Here thou mayſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand how, and in what manner, Faith, Hope and Love are poured forth or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veighed into our Souls, why becauſe the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> who is the true Living Water ſheds himſelf abroad in our hearts, and ſo cauſeth them to flow forth, which af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards farther diffuſe themſelves into manifold other Vertues and Graces, firſt to thoſe that have them, and afterwards alſo to others that ſee their Works. And laſtly, as the ſtream is not the Original of the Spring, nor the Spring or Fountain the Original of the hidden Water, ſo neither can our Works be the Original of Faith, Hope and Charity, nor Faith, Hope and Charity be the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal or Cauſe of the Indwelling of the <hi>Holy Ghost.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="94" facs="tcp:152164:57"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. X.</hi> The Love to God that is in us, is begotten and born of the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of God's Love towards us.</head>
                     <p>NOthing can be conceived more proper and efficacious to beget Love, than Love; therefore 'tis that <hi>God</hi> then and there only appears moſt amiable and love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly unto us, when his unutterable Love to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards us, his ſurpaſſing Benefits and the Merits of Chriſt are pourtrayed and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed on the heart, when in his Light we diſcover, how our Heavenly Father, when we were as yet his Enemies, gave his only begotten Son to come down into Fleſh, into this mortal Life, yea into the bittereſt Suffering and Death for us. But now this Revelation, Manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Impreſſion on the heart, cannot be performed by any one, but by <hi>God</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, who has the hearts of all in his own hand, and inclines the Will according to his own pleaſure. Our dear Lord Chriſt is that flinty Rock that ſtrikes Fire, but yet doth not give it forth, except it be forc'd from him with the ſtrong Iron. Chriſt
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:152164:57"/>alſo is the Rock that gives forth Water, yet not till it be ſmitten with <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Rod. His Holy Life, his Suffering and Death give forth no kindling, no infla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming fire, except they be ſtir'd and ſtruck with the eternal, unchangeable, conſtant, ſtrong Love of <hi>God,</hi> in which he im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutably and without repentance has ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted thoſe, who ſhall be the Inheritors of his Eternal Joy; for no ſtriking helps, nor kindles any fire, except it fall into the true, catching Tinder of thoſe Souls, whom <hi>God</hi> from Eternity hath determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to favour with his Grace, to ſanctifie and ſave them. For elſe, ſtrike who will, the Rock never gives fire, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently neither doth the Tinder catch it. But when <hi>God</hi> ſtrikes the Rock in the heart of his choſen, then it preſently gives forth fire, then the dead Coals become live Coals, the black Tinder looks glorious like the burniſh'd Gold, and the cold fire becomes ſhining and flaming in that Love; which is kindled by <hi>God</hi>'s Love. Thus Love proceeds and ſprings from Love, that is from the Love of <hi>God</hi> to us proceeds our reciprocal Love to him. So likewiſe neither doth this Rock give forth
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:152164:58"/>Water, except it be ſtruck with the Rod of <hi>Moſes;</hi> ever flowing ſtreams of Grace do not flow from Chriſt, neither doth he appear in the higheſt degree lovely and amiable, friendly and kind, in that he was ſcourged, crown'd with Thorns, mocked and crucifyed, but becauſe the merciful Lord God, the true <hi>Moſes,</hi> the Great Law-giver of the Law of Love, out of pure Love to us, or as the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> (<hi>chap.</hi> 53.5, 8.) ſaith, for our ſakes, hath ſtruck and ſmitten him, to the end that nothing but Love might flow from him, and that the ſubſtantial and eſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Love, which is God himſelf, (which is given unto us before all gifts and graces without any merit of ours for Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs) might through the Holy Ghoſt flow through and wholely penetrate our hearts. From all which we may gather this Concluſion, that to love God above all, is a meer pure Grace and Favour a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all our Arts or Abilities, and above all our Works and Merits.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="11" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="97" facs="tcp:152164:58"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. XI.</hi> To love God above all things is not vouchſaved to all Beloved ones in the ſame Meaſure or Degree.</head>
                     <p>TO love <hi>God</hi> above all things is to love him Savingly, now foraſmuch as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in Saving Love, there be higher and lower, greater and leſs degrees, it will not be in vain or unprofitable, to make men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſaid difference or diverſity. There are ſome in this Love of <hi>God</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all things, that are called <hi>Incipientes i.e.</hi> Beginners; others <hi>Proficientes</hi> Profici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents, or goers forward, and ſome again, <hi>Perfecti,</hi> that are arrived to the Perfection of it. Of which three ſorts, the firſt love <hi>God</hi> leaſt, the ſecond more, the third or laſt, moſt of all; yet all of them Love, him above all things; for did they love any thing more than <hi>God,</hi> or equal with him, their Love would rather be Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred of <hi>God,</hi> becauſe therein they do not render him his true and due Honour, as, <hi>Gods</hi> Love ſaith. Men indeed may build Straw, Hay and Wood, Gold, Silver and Pretious Stones upon the Rock; but for
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:152164:59"/>all that the Foundation doth not ſuffer it ſelf to be ſhaken or removed. Chriſt muſt ſtill be Chriſt, and <hi>God</hi> muſt be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved as <hi>God,</hi> that is above all things, this is the true Foundation of all Love, and good Deſires, and this is common to all true Lovers of what rank ſoever. But the Reaſon of the diverſity of ſome lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving more, ſome leſs, ſome in a higher, and others in a lower degree, is this, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>Gods</hi> kind and amiable Manifeſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of himſelf, doth not act neceſſarily like Nature, according to its utmoſt Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and Ability, but more or leſs, as the Holy Ghoſt pleaſeth, and how, and when, he pleaſeth. Therefore to Love God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all things, is not only <hi>Free Grace,</hi> but every degree of Love is ſo likewiſe.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="12" type="chapter">
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. XII.</hi> How, or in what manner, the <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginner</hi> loves God above all things.</head>
                     <p>THE firſt degree of Love manifeſts it ſelf in this manner, when the Love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs of <hi>God</hi> is ſo deeply imprinted on the
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:152164:59"/>heart, that a Man begins to love <hi>God</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all things, then ſuch a Love infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libly brings along with it a loathing or diſlike of whatſoever is contrary to <hi>God,</hi> as of all deadly Sin, and more eſpecially of <hi>Pride,</hi> whereby Man takes upon him to place himſelf on even ground with, or above <hi>God;</hi> which every Man does, when he loves himſelf as much as, or more than <hi>God.</hi> This Love brings along with it Humility in Honour, Temperance in Luſts, and holy Fear, not ſuch as Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants ſtand in of their Maſter, but ſuch as young Children have for their Father. In theſe <hi>Beginners</hi> there is a mixture of Fear and Love, and a Conjunction of Heavenly and Earthly Deſires; they love many things together with <hi>God.</hi> Therefore the vertue or goodneſs of theſe, conſiſts only in this, that the Love of <hi>God</hi> that is in them, continually brings forth Heavenly Deſires, and that tho' they love <hi>God,</hi> together with other things, yet they love him above and more than them. Wherefore alſo the <hi>Beginner</hi> falls often into many leſſer Sins, by the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light he takes in Temporal Profit, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Pleaſure, and into ſtrong Fears
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:152164:60"/>and Apprehenſions of Temporal Loſſes and Trouble, finds alſo in himſelf ſtrong Inclinations to Deadly Sins, ſo that often he is ready to ſin, but that the Friendly and Lovely Perception of <hi>God</hi> in his heart doth hinder him. Wherefore it ſtill appears, that whatſoever the Love of <hi>God</hi> above all things, begets or brings forth in the Heart, is nothing elſe but meer Grace.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="13" type="chapter">
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. XIII.</hi> How the <hi>Proficient</hi> Loves God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all things.</head>
                     <p>MOreover it oft happens, that <hi>God</hi> from Heaven doth manifeſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf yet more friendly and amiably to the Heart, and thereby inflames the Will to that degree, that now the Soul doth not only love <hi>God</hi> above all things, but alſo make uſe of all other things in ſubordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and with reference to the Love of <hi>God,</hi> in all things aiming at his Praiſe and Glory. Such an one is more concern'd how he may pleaſe <hi>God,</hi> than about Sins diſpleaſing of him. Now he to whom it
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:152164:60"/>is given to love <hi>God</hi> in this Degree, or to ſpeak more exact, he in whom the Holy Ghoſt thus loves, in him this Love is immediately followed by the Love of Righteouſneſs, great Strength and Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage of Mind, a Liberal Heart, Prudent Converſe, wiſe Purpoſes and Underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings, and other ſuch like Vertues that help to raiſe a Man above himſelf. I have ſaid that Man being ſo highly excited and moved with the Divine Kindneſs and Lovelineſs, doth love <hi>God</hi> in this manner, or rather that the Holy Ghoſt thus loves in him, to the end that no body might attribute his Proficiency or riſing higher to himſelf, but appropriate and impute it to <hi>God</hi> alone. Even as Chriſt inſtructed his Diſciples, and in them all of us: <hi>When ye ſhall be brought before Kings and Governors for my ſake, take no thought how, or what ye ſhall ſpeak: for it ſhall be given you in that ſame hour what ye ſhall ſpeak. For it is not ye that ſpeak, but the Spirit of your Father that ſpeaketh in you.</hi> Mat. 10.18, 19, 20. Theſe are the Words of Eternal Truth. Now if it be true, that he does not ſpeak, whom we ſee moving his Tongue and Lips, whoſe Voice we hear,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:152164:61"/>and perceive his Breath, why ſhould not we then for the ſame reaſon appropriate and impute the Love we feel in our hearts to <hi>God</hi> alone, acknowledging it to be his only. The moving or motion is from the Holy Ghoſt, but the perceiving of it is ours, as when any one tickleth us, the Tickling is anothers, but the Senſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion it produces is our own. From all which it appears, that the Love of <hi>Profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients,</hi> together with the Vertues flowing from it are meer Grace, as well as that of the <hi>Beginner.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="14" type="chapter">
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. XIV.</hi> How the <hi>Perfect</hi> Lover loves God above all things.</head>
                     <p>HE is called <hi>Perfect</hi> in Love, to whom <hi>God</hi> manifeſts and repreſents him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſo kind, ſo ſweet, and ſo amiable, that he becomes wholely of the mind, that there is nothing lovely but <hi>God,</hi> nothing kind, ſweet and friendly but <hi>God.</hi> Such a Man as this loatheth and is burthen'd with himſelf, hateth this Life, and longs
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:152164:61" rendition="simple:additions"/>for Death, that nothing might hinder him in his Love. Wherefore alſo ſtrange and wonderful Works proceed from ſuch an one, all which <hi>God</hi> by Love works in him. He is full of Joy, Peace and Reſt; he doth not trouble himſelf about either Heaven or Hell, Angel or Devil, Friend or Foe, he hates Father and Mother, Wife and Children, Brothers and Siſters, yea even his own Soul, and loſeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf wholely and altogether in this World, that he may find himſelf in his Beloved. He is got beyond ſelf chooſing and his own Works, and only waits upon what <hi>God</hi> will be pleaſed to chooſe, think, ſpeak and work in him, with total, profound Obedience and perfect Reſignation. He lives even as if he lived not, for his Spirit cleaves ſo faſt to <hi>God,</hi> that he becomes one Spirit with him. Fear takes no place in him, his Labour is without Wearineſs, and his Sufferings are become his Joy, Triumph and Exultation. But to whom are we to aſcribe all theſe great, ſtrange and wonderful Works? To Man? Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, no, That be far from any Chriſtian Mind. God himſelf is the Worker, the Holy Ghoſt is that Fire, which totally
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:152164:62"/>conſumes Man, and burns him to Aſhes, yea wholely and altogether annihilates, or brings him to nothing, that ſo he alone may remain the All, in All, in him and in All things. Let every Soul in this Station carefully take heed not to attribute or appropriate any thing of activity or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perativeneſs to her ſelf: But let her re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce in her moſt faithful and moſt lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <hi>God;</hi> who hath drawn her out of her ſelf, and hath of <hi>Free Grace,</hi> favoured her to live in himſelf, in his own Spirit. And therefore let ſuch a Soul examine her ſelf, whether ſhe finds thoſe Fruits in her, which ſpring from the foreſaid high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt degree of Love, whether or no ſhe be that Tree, which <hi>God</hi> himſelf hath plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; for whatſoever <hi>God</hi> hath not planted muſt be plucked up by the Roots, caſt away and burnt in the Fire. Wherefore the Great Duty of the Soul in this ſtate, is, to have an Eye to two things; more eſpecially, the one is, that ſhe be never without good Thoughts, Words, or Works; the other is, that ſhe in her in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>activity, or ceaſing from her Works, do find her ſelf to be wrought upon by the Holy Ghoſt, from whence proceeds
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:152164:62"/>the Divine Adoption (as St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells us, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.14.) for <hi>they who are Led</hi> and actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated <hi>by the Spirit of God, are the Children of God,</hi> and <hi>cannot Sin,</hi> an St. <hi>John</hi> ſaith, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.6, 9. <hi>For the Holy Ghoſt bears wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs with their Spirit, that they are the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God, Heirs of God, and Joint-Heirs with our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, Rom.</hi> 8.15, 16. He who hath this witneſs in himſelf, he doth not own his Works to be his own, but the Holy Ghoſts, to whom it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to ſin, and therefore wholly leaves Nature, and acknowledgeth himſelf to be a Child of Grace; as having by the new Birth paſſed out of Nature into Grace.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="15" type="chapter">
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. XV.</hi> The Degrees of the Love of God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all things have a mutual Subordination and Reſpect to one another; but yet are not all gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by God in the ſame Order.</head>
                     <p>FRom Imperfection according to the order of Nature, we advance and go on to Perfection; and nothing grows
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:152164:63"/>Great, which has not before been little, in all caſes where the order of Nature is kept. But when Perfection comes from abroad, and is a free gift, then it is whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the Power of him that beſtows it, to give it in a lower or higher Degree, as pleaſeth him beſt. For he that hath a mind to beſtow a thouſand pounds upon any one, of his free Will, he may at firſt give him one pound, at another ten, at another an hundred, and ſo on; or if he pleaſe, he may invert this Order, and give at firſt an hundred, next ten, and afterwards one; or elſe may give the whole thouſand pounds at once, as beſt liketh him. Foraſmuch therefore, as to love God above all things, is a free Gift of the Holy Ghoſt, it depends wholely of his Will to beſtow the ſame in the higheſt or loweſt Degree, ſooner or la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or all the Degrees of it together and at once, according as it ſeems good in in his Eyes; for notwithſtanding the <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginners</hi> Love be in it ſelf inferior and leſs, the <hi>Proficients,</hi> better; and the Love of thoſe who are <hi>Perfect,</hi> beſt of all; yet is it one and the ſame thing with him to make a Sinner <hi>Perfect</hi> in Love at the firſt,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:152164:63"/>as to make him a <hi>Beginner,</hi> according as frequently he has done. Thus verily, we ſee, that the Repentance of <hi>Paul, Peter</hi> and <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> were <hi>perfect</hi> Works, in which <hi>Paul</hi> was caught up into the third Heaven, <hi>Peter</hi> became melted into ſweet tears of Love, and <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> with Joy of heart waſhed the feet of God with her Tears, and wip'd them with the hair of her head, notwithſtanding that Repentance in it ſelf be the work of <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginners.</hi> Many Perſons likewiſe experience in themſelves, that at their firſt taking leave of Sin by true Repentance, they find in themſelves a readineſs to forſake them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and all the World, which is a Work of <hi>Perfect</hi> Love, and yet two or three days after, it may be, the ſame perſons find great difficulty and oppoſition to deny them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in parting with the leaſt part of their Goods, or ſome filthy Luſt, which is the weak and defective Work of <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginners.</hi> Sometimes at the Beginning of our Converſion, we are able to bear an hundred weight, which belongs to thoſe that are <hi>Proficients,</hi> when, it may be, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time after we are not able to bear a pound weight, which is a ſtate beneath
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:152164:64"/>that of <hi>Beginners.</hi> The reaſon of this al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration, is, becauſe we do not bear our burthens by our own ſtrength, but by the Might and Power of the moſt High, who imparts the ſame unto us when, and how, he will, not according to our, but his own, good Pleaſure and Liking. This diſcovers the great Folly of thoſe, who think by their good Deeds to move and incline <hi>God</hi> according to their Will and Pleaſure; who, in their own conceit, would make themſelves lovely and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to <hi>God,</hi> and allure <hi>God</hi> to them by their Vertue and Goodneſs, as they lure Hawks with a Bait; by which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion, they rob the Divine Mercy of it's due Priviledg and Prerogative, and carry blaſted Oats to Market; they would fain purchaſe Gold with Dung, and be ſaved by their own Righteouſneſs, and to defend their Folly, alledg the Say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the Holy Fathers, which they never yet underſtood. And are alſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremely diſpleaſed with thoſe, who cannot comply with them in this their Folly. O Folly beyond all Folly! To miſtake about the number of the Stars, the Height of Heaven, the Depth of the Sea,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:152164:64" rendition="simple:additions"/>and ſuch like is no great damage or loſs; but to miſtake in thoſe things that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern our Salvation, is a Loſs ineſtimable and irreparable, and more eſpecially in the Love of <hi>God:</hi> for he that miſtakes in this Love, miſtakes in all things, that are neceſſary to Salvation; whereas he who is not miſtaken in this, cannot err in any thing, that of neceſſity condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth to Salvation. Would to <hi>God</hi> that all the Books were loſt, wherein Men have taught us to practice Vertues, ſo that Love alone were but found by us; for then every one would do what he ought. But foraſmuch as the Divine Love only flows forth from <hi>Gods</hi> Love revealed and manifeſted to us, it for the moſt part happens, that we through our vehement earneſtneſs and eager purſuit after her, hinder our ſelves from relliſhing her ſweet Savour, which is beſt taſted and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, when we are ſilent, and intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, inwardly attentive, when we o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen our Mouths wide, expecting the Heavenly Food; when we work or do neither Good nor Evil, but attend the Working of the Holy Spirit in us. In this manner, <hi>David hearkned and heard what
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:152164:65"/>God ſpake in him, and found him ſpeaking Peace. He opened his Mouth wide, and experienc'd Gods filling it; was ſilent and waited upon God, and received Incomes of Spiritual Strength and Power, Pſ.</hi> 81.10.40. 1.85.8. For <hi>the Almighty VVord</hi> (ſaith the Wiſe King, <hi>Wiſd</hi> 18.14,15.) <hi>comes not down from Heaven, his Royal Throne,</hi> nor ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers it ſelf to be heard, <hi>till all things be in quiet ſilence.</hi> Therefore for a concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, we muſt above all things labour and endeavour for inward ſtillneſs and quiet of Heart, and to reduce our Prayer, and other outward and inward Exerciſes to Reſt and Silence, that ſo we may hear the Heavenly Voice of <hi>God,</hi> and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive his Lovely Motions. Thus thou ſeeſt, how our good <hi>God</hi> permits himſelf to be overtaken by a ſoft or ſlow Pace, but never by Running, according as we read concerning the Divine Spouſe, <hi>Cant.</hi> 3.1, 2, 4. <hi>c.</hi> 5.2, 3, 4, 5, 6. That when ſhe laid down on her Bed, and had no Deſire after her Bridegroom, but rather ſeem'd to be troubled at his knocking, yet was this the time he took to manifeſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in all Friendlineſs and Love towards her, whereas when ſhe run out after him, he hid himſelf from her.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="16" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="111" facs="tcp:152164:65"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. XVI.</hi> The Degrees of the Love of God alter and are changed, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Will and Pleaſure of the Self-ſubſiſting Love of God, ſuitable to what he knows to be moſt <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſeful for Men.</head>
                     <p>TO Love <hi>God</hi> above all things there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is a perpetual and conſtant Work, always abiding the ſame, as long as the Lover abides, in the true Love, yet not always at the ſame Height, or in the ſame Degree, but ſometimes more, and at other times leſs, as <hi>God</hi> knows it will be moſt Profitable for the Beloved Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. To <hi>Paul</hi> was given <hi>a thorn in the Fleſh, an Angel of Satan to buffet him, that he might not be exalted above meaſure by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the abundance of Revelations</hi> vouchſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed unto him, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.7. And on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hand we ſee, the <hi>Robber was aſſured of his part in Paradice, Luk.</hi> 23.43. and had a clear ſight given him, that he was a Child of Salvation, and was favoured with a joyful Death, to the end the
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:152164:66"/>Depth of his Sins might not overwhelm him. At one time <hi>Paul</hi> crys out, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.24. <hi>O wretched Man that I am! who ſhall deliver me from this Body of Death?</hi> And not long after we hear him boaſting and triumphing at ſuch a rate as this, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.38, 39. <hi>for I am perſwaded, that neither Death nor Life, nor Angels, nor Principalities, nor Powers, nor things preſent, nor things to come, nor Height, nor Depth, nor any other Creature, ſhall ſeparate me from the Love of God, which is in Chriſt Jeſus our Lord.</hi> This was a <hi>perfect</hi> Word, proceeding from a <hi>perfect</hi> Love. Thus it happens ſtill at this day, that God often in an Hours time, yea in a much ſhorter ſpace, doth oft alter the degrees of Love in us. Sometimes we find in our ſelves a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Elevation of our Minds, with entire and total Reſignation; and ſoon after experience a frightful and doubting Heart, and an unſtable Will, and many are in the ſame Moment comforted again with Courageouſneſs and a Peaceful and Joyful Mind, which makes them break forth with <hi>David,</hi> Pſalm. 56.11. <hi>In God have I put my Truſt, and will not fear what all mine Enemies can do unto me,</hi> So that a
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:152164:66"/>Man here upon Earth, is not conſtant in any degree of Love, but ſometimes is raiſed above himſelf, and at other times ſinks beneath himſelf, according as the Holy Ghoſt draws him. Further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more we are to know to our great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, that the Love which God hath to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards us doth neither admit of encreaſe, dminution; and frequently is doing the very beſt for us, when we leaſt of all perceive or underſtand it. We are alſo for the moſt part moſt ſweet and well pleaſing to him, when he ſeems moſt bitter and harſh to us, here upon Earth, where his Divine Love more exerts its ſelf for our Croſs and Suffering, than for our Joy. Heaven is the place, where God continually manifeſts and diſplays himſelf in everlaſting Joys, not this Earth. Foraſmuch therefore as there is more advantage and profit in Poverty, than in Riches; more in Suffering, than in enjoyment; more in Weeping than in Laughter; more in Hunger than in Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs or Satiety; more in Communion of Suffering, than in Communion of Comfort, it follows, that the Love of God manifeſts it ſelf in a fuller and grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:152164:67"/>Meaſure to us, when it procures us La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation, Sorrow Suffering and Miſery, than when it affords us pleaſure and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light. Wherefore altho' the feeling of that Quiet and Peace of Heart, which is the Portion of thoſe who are <hi>Perfect</hi> in Love, be Sweeter and more delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful; yet is the Love of <hi>Proficients,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in God manifeſts himſelf for the ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and encouraging of the Mind, more profitable for Advantage and Amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Beſides it is far more profitable and advantagious to our Salvation, that we deſpair of our own Strength, than that we confide in our own Works or Labour. For which Cauſe alſo God of his great Grace, doth frequently take away from us the Love of <hi>Proficients,</hi> and drives us into the acknowledgment of our diſability, and into fearfulneſs and deſpairing of our ſelves, to the end that as little helpleſs Children, we might run to him as our only Redeemer, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counting our ſelves nothing; and mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying his Grace and Power alone. When it is thus with us, then from the great Love of God to us ward, the Love of <hi>Beginners</hi> proves of greateſt uſe and
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:152164:67"/>advantage to us; and we do experience by ſo much the more comfort from God, by how much the more we deſpair of our own Power; when we do not truſt in our Strength, nor take upon us to ſtrive and ſtruggle, but only ſix our eye upon the Lifted up Brazen Serpent,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Numb.</hi> 21.6, 7, 8, 9.</note> as in the Figure it is very comfortably held forth to us. When the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were dangerouſly: and mortally hurt, by the poyſonful ſtinging of the Fiery Serpents, God was pleaſed to give them a Brazen Serpent lifted up on a Pole, even a Serpent without Poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon made of Braſs; and whoſoever did only behold the ſame, became immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately healed, and all the Serpents fled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from him without any more ado. Which Figure imports thus much, that there is no more ready or compendious way for a Man to get rid of the Poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of Diabolical Temptation, than when he deſpairs of any oppoſition himſelf can make againſt it, and lays hold only on the Croſs, truſting and confiding in that Fight and Combat, which Chriſt, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Sin, maintained againſt the Sins of
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:152164:68"/>Men, to exterminate the Diabolical Poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and in the ſame came off a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queror and Triumphator: And thus a Chriſtian boaſteth of Chriſt alone, and wholly deſpairs of himſelf. Wherefore it is much better for a Man to commit and reſign himſelf wholly to God, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Praying for this, or the other feel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or Perception of the Divine Love, but that he would order all things ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his own good Pleaſure. When a Man comes to this State, he enjoys a conſtant and abiding Peace, Tranquility and Comfort, founded and bottom'd on the unchangeable Love God bears to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards us, however Dead, Barren or Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy he may find himſelf. But they who will not reſt, ſave in the higheſt degrees of Love; and who do not believe God is with them, when they do not feel in themſelves the Sweetneſs of his Love, or at leaſt ſome Comfort and Solace of his Spirit; ſuch as theſe have no conſtant abiding Comfort here on Earth, and are in Eminent Danger both as to Soul and Body.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="17" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="117" facs="tcp:152164:68" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. XVII.</hi> That all things work together for the beſt of the Elect, that Love God above all things.</head>
                     <p>ALL things, and all Creatures are theirs, who belong to Chriſt and are his, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, 1 Cor. 3. <hi>v.</hi> 21, 22, 23. <hi>The Apoſtles, the World, Life, Death, Things preſent and things to come, and in a Word all Creatures are his, who himſelf is Chriſts, and Chriſt,</hi> without a mean, <hi>is Gods,</hi> but we are his, through or by means of Chriſt. Wherefore al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the Elect Soul, is by means of Chriſt, ſo highly Seated in Gods favour, that all Evil, yea, even Sin it ſelf, is not only not hurtful to her, but alſo conducive and helpful in the hand of God her great Phyſitian to her beſt State. Verily a true Chriſtian is a Miraculous Creature of God, with whom God from Eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, in the higheſt Love, has ſo intimate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly United himſelf, that tho' (as <hi>David</hi> ſaith, Pſalm. 89.30, 31, 32.) <hi>He for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the Divine Law, and walks not in his Judgments, tho he prophane his Statutes, and
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:152164:69"/>keep not his Commandments, yet God, for all this, will only Chaſtiſe him Temporally, and not utterly take away his loving kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs from him;</hi> So that even his Sin muſt be helpful to his Salvation. For what God hath once determined, can never fail, and whatſoever he hath once pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, muſt Eternally be true: whom <hi>God</hi> Loves and Favours, to him Heaven and Hell, Good and Evil muſt be helpful and advantagious. And for this Reaſon it is that we are very Subject to be mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken and confounded in our Reflecting on the Works of other Men, and find that we are not able in the leaſt to paſs a true Judgment or Eſtimate, what is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable or hurtful to Men, foraſmuch as we find by experience, that <hi>God</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times out of great and faithful Love, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits him that ſtands, to fall. Who doubts but that <hi>Peters</hi> Fall, wherein he denied his Lord and Maſter, was far more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable and advantagious for him, than to have continued and perſevered in his ſelf-confidence. Our <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>God</hi> has a greater Intereſt, and is more concerned to manifeſt and diſplay the glory of his own Grace, Mercy, than to maintain
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:152164:69" rendition="simple:additions"/>and keep up our Righteouſneſs. His leaſt ſuffering was ſufficient to reconcile his Heavenly Father to us, to Juſtifie, to Preſerve, or make us perſevere in Righteouſneſs, and to ſave us; but this would not have been ſufficient to hold forth the unmeaſurableneſs of his Love, or the unalterableneſs of his Mercy. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Paul</hi> tells us, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.32. <hi>That God hath concluded all under <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelief and Sin, that he might have Mercy upon all.</hi> If you take away Sin, who then will be able clearly to underſtand that Gods Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy is above, and beyond all his Works; or that Chriſt the true Son of <hi>God</hi> is the Redeemer of the World? Which no other way could ever have been ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted, but by his unalterable Love, and by that great inſtance of his Tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Pity and Compaſſion to us miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Sinners. And therefore <hi>Gregory</hi> calls Sin Salutary or Saving, becauſe by Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Mercy it procur'd us ſo glorious a Saviour and Redeemer. Foraſmuch then as <hi>God</hi> makes uſe of Sin for the advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his Divine Glory, it is no longer any Wonder that he makes the ſame al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo advantagious to the Sinner. But we
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:152164:70"/>muſt not argue from hence, that if it be ſo, we may therefore freely ſin, without Danger, by no means; but on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary it is our Duty at all times, with our utmoſt Diligence and Strength, to avoid Sin, as we would the moſt deadly Poyſon; for to cover Sin with Mercy is the Work of <hi>God</hi> alone. 'Tis he only that can bring good out of Evil; we can fall of our ſelves, but not riſe again of our ſelves; this reſts only in the gracious Mercifulneſs of <hi>God,</hi> which excells and ſurmounts all his Works.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="18" type="chapter">
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. XVIII.</hi> Whoſoever hath not received the Love of God above all things, to him all the Temporal good things that God affords him, are of no Profit.</head>
                     <p>ST. <hi>Paul,</hi> faith, 1 Cor, 13, 1, 2, 3. <hi>Tho' I ſpeak with the Tongues of Men and Angels, and have not Love or Charity, I am become like a ſounding-Braſs, or a loud Cymbol; and tho' I have the gift of
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:152164:70"/>Propheſie, and underſtand all Mysteries and Knowledge; and tho I have all Faith, ſo that I could remove Mountains, and have no Charity, I am nothing: Moreover tho I beſtow all my Goods to feed the Poor, and though I give my Body to be burned, if I have not Charity it profiteth me nothing.</hi> Yea, what's ſtill more, where Love is not, it is to a perſons Hurt and Loſs, that ever he was born a Man, and the higheſt Gifts or Benefits God hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed upon him ſerve only for his grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter condemnation. It had been better for <hi>Judas,</hi> he had neverbeen born (as Chriſt himſelf teſtifies) that he had never been an Apoſtle, that he had never wrought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Miracles, that he had never ſeen or heard of Jeſus, and had never eaten the ſweet Food with him at the ſame Table, than that after ſuch great and ineſtimable Favours received, he ſhould become his Betrayer, ſell him and deliver him to the <hi>Jews.</hi> From whence we may take notice, that our deareſt Lord God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtows that often in his Wrath, which he denies in his Love. From whence alſo follows, that the higher the Gifts are, we receive from God; the more they engage us to the Duty of loving God
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:152164:71"/>above all things, tho they cannot make us to Love God ſo; and therefore are rather Poyſon than Gifts, if Love does not come along with them, neither can they certainly aſſure us of that love, wherewith God loves us to Salvation. Moreover theſe Gifts when they ate ſeparate from Love, are the cauſe of a puft up Spirit, Pround Mind, cenſorious judging, arrogant Actions, imprudent Behaviour and converſe, Self conceited<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Hypocriſie, and Contempt of the ſimple and ſingle hearted, and other ſuch like. Wherefore alſo Jeſus ſaid to his Diſciples, when they boaſted themſelves becauſe of the High gifts of God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed upon them; and more eſpicially becauſe the Devils were ſubject and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to them through his Name: <hi>I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held Satan as Lightning fall from Heaven:</hi> and added this following Leſſon; true it is, <hi>I have given you Power to tread upon Serpents and Scorpions, and over all the Power of the Enemy; notwithſtanding for this rejoyce not, nor in particular for that the Evil Spirits are ſubject to you, but ratherrejoyce becauſe your Names are written in Heaven.</hi> Luke 10.17, 18, 19. It is very proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:152164:71"/>that <hi>Judas,</hi> as well as <hi>Peter,</hi> healed the fick, caſt out Devils, and wrought other Miracles, but foraſmuch as he wanted Love, all this was of no avail to him. Wherefore it behoves us always to walk with Fear and Trembling, and to be ſo much the more humble, as we enjoy more of theſe Divine Gifts and Graces, whereof we muſt give an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count to God, how we have employ'd them.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="19" type="chapter">
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. XIX.</hi> Whoſoever hath a true Love to God, he undoubtedly keeps all his Commands.</head>
                     <p>A true Mark of the Love of God, is the fulfilling of the Commands of God, according to the Doctrine of the Wiſeman; for love begets likeneſs, and conformity, makes one Heart, one Will, one Soul in the Lover and the Beloved. When Love raiſeth her ſelf above her ſelf, ſhe frames her ſelf into the will of her Beloved, and if ſhe ſtoops be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath her ſelf, ſhe moulds all things into
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:152164:72"/>her own likeneſs, and eſteems or values nothing according to its natural goodneſs, but according to her own good liking or pleaſure: And ſo makes that Evil, which was by God created good in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. He who loves God above all things, is well pleaſed with whatſoever is well pleaſing to God, and is troubled at every thing that diſpleaſeth him, and therefore he loves Righteouſneſs and hates Iniquity, does that which is Good and avoids Evil: I ſay he does that which is good, tho not always according to the works of the Law, yet always in confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity with the end of the Law; for it happens ſometimes, that a man in doing contrary to the works of the Law, yet does that which is right and good with reference to the end of the Law. Now the end of the Law is the Love of God above all things, with which no manner of Evil doing may conſiſt. So that he who truly loves God, keeps all that God hath commanded him, even wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſoever is contain'd in the Divine Word, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ccor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Doctrine of St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> who expreſſeth himſelf in theſe following Words: <q>Love but, and then do what
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:152164:72"/>thou wilt: Art thou ſilent? be ſilent for Love; doſt thou cry aloud? Cry aloud for love: Doſt thou reprove? Reprove for Love: Doſt thou recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile? Reconcile out of Love:</q> keep but this Root in thy heart, even true Divine Love and Charity, and than nothing but what's good, can ever come from thee, nothing can be done by thee, but what is ſaving, or tends to Salvation. Wherefore Men can never be Divinely taught by any one, ſave only in the School of Love, with her alone are found the doers of of the Divine Word; all other Arts and Learning whatſoever make nothing but Hearers only. To this Art of Arts even the Love of God, Parents ſhould draw and allure their Children; The Maſters, their Schollars; the ſpiritual Paſtors, their Sheep; or rather the Sheep of Chriſt. Whatſoever it is they teach be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides this, is nothing but Labour and Vexation of Spirit: Neither indeed is there any other Art neceſſary to Salvation. Yet it is true too, that no body can ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually teach this Divine Art of Love but God himſelf, as before hath been
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:152164:73"/>declar'd, wherefore aiſo our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt forbids us, to look out for any other Maſter, for to attain the Art of Salvation, ſave himſelf alone.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="20" type="chapter">
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. XX.</hi> They who love God in the Higheſt degree, do not think the Yoak and Burthen of Chriſt to be Heavy or Troubleſome, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Eaſie and Light.</head>
                     <p>ALas! How many heavy and intolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Burthens do we ſee, which in this miſerable State, the Love of this World and our Fleſhly uncleanneſs, and corrupt inclinations, make very eaſie and deſirable. In order to get Riches we ſee the Merchant expoſeth himſelf to the Raging Sea, breaks his Sleep, and ſhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens his Life: To arrive to Honour and Dignity a man abandons himſelf to a continual ſlavery at Court, and to all that which is hurtful and grievous to Soul and Body: For the ſake of Luſt and impure Love, more eſpecially that
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:152164:73"/>which men bear to Women, and Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men to Men, what intolerable burthens are not readily, willingly and gladly Born? For Love, alas! is ſo faſt rooted and riveted in our Fleſh and Blood, that beyond any other thing whatſoever no body without the ſpecial Grace and Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of God, can any longer moderate, curb or reſtrain it, much leſs quite root it our. The inclination of the heart brought the Love of Women along with it into Paradiſe, and we ſuck the ſame from our Mothers Breaſts; yea we take it from our Mothers hearts, whilſt we are yet hid in the Womb. <hi>For the ſake of Women</hi> (ſaith<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Zorobabel,</hi> as we find it in 1 <hi>Eſdras</hi> 4.14, 15, 16.) <hi>Men forſake and abandon their Honour, Lives and Goods, yea Vertue and Reaſon, and become captiva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, yea ſenſeleſs and diſtracted by Reaſon of the Love they bear to them.</hi> This inborn and inbred Love, neither Frock nor Cowl, neither Church nor Convent, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Cell nor Dungeon can keep out, except the grace of <hi>God,</hi> through our Lord Jeſus Chriſt come in to our help: But indeed when that once comes, the work is Light and Eaſie; for if that
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:152164:74"/>once ſweetly impreſſeth and ingraves the unutterable Love of God on the heart, then all other Loves muſt pack up and be gone; and the more clearly ſhe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſts her ſelf, and the more amiably ſhe imageth or forms her ſelf in the Soul; ſo much the more ſpeedily muſt Fleſh and Blood ſink and periſh. Yea ſometimes ſhe appears ſo ſweet to the Soul, that all Creatures become diſtaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to it. Here it is that our Iron-hard heart becomes ſoft, pliant, and yielding, the heavy and troubleſome yoak be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes ſweet and eaſie, and inſuportable Burthen, light and pleaſurable, and all this becauſe God doth amiably move and affect our Spirits. VVould you have me Communicate this Art to you, and tell you how it is able to perform theſe great things? Pray reſolve me firſt of a matter which is a thouſand times leſs: How comes it to paſs that he heavy lumpiſh Iron runs to the embraces of the Load Stone, and why as ſoon as a diſh or baſon, wherein Iron lies, is touched with the Load ſtone, doth the Iron raiſe it ſelf, and begin to move that way to which the Load Stone draws it. Doſt
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:152164:74"/>thou ſay the Stone is able to do this, tho thou canſt not tell me how, or by what means? Then wonder no more how the Creator of Nature can ſo freely and powerfully move his own work, or how the unutterable Lovelineſs of God taſted and felt in the Heart, doth ſublime and raiſe the ſpirit in Love, kindle it, melt it, and make it triumphantly joyful, and full of Jubilee. Doth the ſtone draw the Iron to it ſelf, without ſo much as touching it, how much more then muſt needs the moſt Rocky and obdurate Soul, being touched by the Eternal Heavenly Load-ſtone, be raiſed above it ſelf, and run into the Embraces of this powerful Drawer?<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Cantic.</hi> 1.4.</note> Or how can it be otherwiſe, but that after this taſte of the tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Divine ſweetneſs, all Tribulation and Suffering ſtrewed over with this Sugar muſt needs become ſweet and deſirable? Or how is it poſſible but that all the ſweetneſs of the Love, oppoſite to this, muſt needs loſe its taſte and become bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and loathſome; ſeeing the common Proverb aſſures us, that to him who rel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſheth the <hi>Spirit,</hi> the <hi>Fleſh</hi> becomes di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſteful
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:152164:75"/>and abominable. For the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and Property of the Holy Spirit of the ſelf-ſubſiſting Love of God is this, that whereſoever ſhe touches, ſhe draws and allures; where ſhe is relliſhed, ſhe drives and impells; where ſhe is felt and experienced, ſhe rejoyceth the Heart. Moreover ſhe has this particular proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that ſhe robs the Fleſh of all its ſweetneſs, like as the Meridian Bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Sun, diſcountenances and darkens the Light of a Candle. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore ſhe hath this alſo amongſt the reſt of her properties that ſhe ſweetens all pains and griefs; comforts and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves Miſery and Wretchedneſs, reſtores all weakneſs, makes all labour light and eaſie, turns weeping into laughter, and ſorrow into joy. He that experimentally finds her, rejoyceth to ſuffer for the ſake of Chriſt, from his very heart deſires to bear the Croſs with Chriſt, and longs for the Fire of Temptation, that therein his Love, being tried, and refined from all Droſs, may purely and nakedly cleave to God, and therefore cries out with the divine Spouſe: <hi>Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>tic.</hi> 4.16. <hi>Ariſe thou North wind, and come on Eaſt wind, and
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:152164:75"/>blow upon my Garden, that my Spices may flow forth and give their ſweet Odour:</hi> As if ſhe had ſaid; come Temptation from all quarters, try and prove my Vertues and Graces, that they may become pure Gold, and be for the amendment and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dification of all that hear or ſee them. O Holy and Divine Spirit! O ſweeteſt Gueſt and Inmate of the Soul! O only life of men! He that wants thee, tho' alive is dead before God; and he that hath got thee, can never die with God, tho the world be carrying him forth to his grave! Thou art far more neceſſary to the Soul, then the Soul is to the Body! VVhere thou art not, there the outward dying is the beginning of Eternal death, but where thou art, of Eternal Life! In thee moſt Holy God we are, in thee we live, in thee we are ſavingly moved, and all this from the Merits and Satisfaction of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, the only Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer of the VVorld, in whom the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>utterable Mercy of God, and over great Love to us, is ſo clearly manifeſted, and through thee, O Holy Ghoſt, ſo plainly i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maged and deeply imprinted in our hearts, that we cannot look for any
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:152164:76"/>thing elſe but Love from the Father, Son and Spirit; ſo that it is now no more poſſible for us to take any ſtrange <hi>God</hi> for our <hi>God,</hi> than it is poſſible for any one elſe to ſhew us ſuch tranſcendent and unmeaſurable Mercy, Kindneſs and Love, as thou haſt made us partakers of. It is poſſible, and it hath oft happened, that even wicked Men have wrought Miracles, being the ſame thing Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture teſtifies, that Antichriſt ſhall do at his coming. It is alſo poſſible, that the Enemies of God may in outward Gifts of Charity ſhew themſelves more liberal to the Eyes of Men, than ever thou haſt done, and to make others by their Liberality rich and powerful and ſuch like. But all theſe are but uncertain ſigns and marks of the right true Love. To ſuffer and die for the ſake of the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved Object, is a true and infallible ſign of Love; when this is done for Gods ſake, it ſhews a Love ſufficient to Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and if it be done for the ſake of a Friend, then is it an expreſſion of the higheſt degree of Human Love, as the Lord Jeſus witneſſeth. <hi>No Man can have greater Love than this, that he lay down his
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:152164:76"/>life for his friend</hi> Joh. 15.31. But if this Love riſe get higher, even to that degree as to make a Man willing to ſuffer and die for his Enemy, then is it a certain Mark of the Love of God alone. VVe read of Antichriſt, that he ſhall do his utmoſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour and diligence, as far as is poſſible, to appear outwardly like to Chriſt in Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, VVorks of VVonder, and in all his other Actions and Behaviour; yea to be more kind and beneficent in outward Gifts and Liberality. He will, as was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hinted, by his Liberality make thoſe Rich and Powerful that believe in him, and will alſo draw to his Party ſuch as are Rich and Powerful, with rigour and ſeverity, and by fear compel them; for he will horribly afflict, torment and put to Death, ſuch as will not believe in him, But it will never pleaſe him to ſuffer for his Enemies, and to die for thoſe that hate him, by which it appears, that his Love is ſo far from being the true Divine Love, that it is not ſo much as the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Degree of Human Love. VVhere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore alſo all theſe pompous Shews of his Love, will be of no force with the Elect of God to deceive them. Out of Chriſt
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:152164:77"/>alone, as was ſaid before, the higheſt Love of God breaks forth and manifeſts it ſelf; out of him alone flow forth the waters of Grace. Neither is there any other Name under Heaven, wherein, and whereby, we may be ſaved, ſave only the ſweeteſt Name <hi>Jeſu,</hi> to whom alone therefore we point and direct all, who are deſirous to be inflamed with the Love of God; for in him alone we meet with all that ought and muſt be ſought for in order to our Salvation.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="21" type="chapter">
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. XXI.</hi> The moſt ſure and certain Sign of all, as well of our entire Love to God, as of his Gracious Love to us, is a perfect Emptineſs or Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inanition of Spirit.</head>
                     <p>THE Heart of a true Lover of God above all things, becomes emptied and void of all Creatures, as ſoon as it is arrived to the degree of <hi>Perfect</hi> Love, ſo that nothing but God, free and alone, remains in his Spirit, all Creatures what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:152164:77"/>ſoever being driven thence. But as long as this is not yet come to paſs in our Souls, all the moſt ſpecious and apparent Signs of Gods dwelling in us are uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, doubtful and to be ſuſpected. But when a Man is become void and empty of himſelf, and all Creatures, when he forgets his own Life, his Merits, his Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; and ſeeks nothing but the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of God, when he is only well plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with his Will, whether it be to his profit or loſs, pleaſing or diſpleaſing, when he daily condemns himſelf, and judgeth no body but himſelf only, then without doubt, God hath taken up his abode in him, and he is top and brimful of God. Wherefore it is a great Grace and Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of God, and not in the leaſt and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of his wrath, when he makes us ſee that there is no Truth, no Faith, no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Love upon Earth; when he mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly diſcovers to a Man, that thoſe who are bound to love him, and to return Good for Evil, do requite him Evil for his Good, Unfaithfulneſs for Love, for this is the true and ready way, by which God from Heaven, through his ſpecial Grace, emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties Fleſh of Fleſh, and faſtens Spirit to
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:152164:78"/>Spirit. Wherefore beg thou of God, that he would be pleaſed to empty thee of thy ſelf and of all Creatures, and take it for a ſpecial, friendly, ſure Token of the Love of God towards, thee, when that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes unloving or diſpleaſing to thee, what at any time, thou haſt loved out of meaſure: For as long as thou cleaveſt to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing, that is not God, thou muſt needs be and continue uncertain, whether God be in thee or no, and tho he may be in thee without thy Knowledg, yet will he never clearly come unto thee, and fully manifeſt himſelf in thee, until all other Loves be rid out of thy heart. This is that which St. <hi>Paul</hi> declares, when he ſaith 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.11, 12, 13. That they who <hi>build Stubble, Hay and Wood upon the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Foundation ſhall indeed be Saved,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they love God above all things, yet no otherwiſe, <hi>but ſo as by Fire,</hi> and that for this reaſon, becauſe they love other things beſides and together with God; but they who <hi>build fine Gold, Silver and pretious Stones,</hi> which are not ſubject to Ruſt, and are refin'd and purged from all droſs, and Refuſe, <hi>upon the true Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, viz.</hi> The Love of God above all
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:152164:78"/>things, they need not to paſs the fire, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they love God only, in the ſame manner as he will be loved of his moſt beloved friends, of whom he requires, according to the Goſpel-Doctrine, that they hate their Father and Mother, their Brothers and Siſters, yea even their own Souls. Now they who do love at this rate, they have eſcap'd from, and are out of the reach of Hell; foraſmuch as they have loved God above all things. They would alſo be rid of all Temporal Sufferings, were it not that their bodily Sufferings, did above meaſure conduce to their Eternal Joy, and that their hearts are to that degree inflamed with the Love of God, that they deſire nothing more or higher, than, as far as is poſſible, to be made conformable to the Suffering Lamb of <hi>God</hi> in all things. They alſo whoſe Love is arrived at this high pitch, have nothing which they cleave unto, but an entire poor Spirit; wherefore alſo they ſuffer nothing here upon Earth, ſave on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Love-Sufferings, as alſo our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus endured no other Sufferings, ſave thoſe of Love. For out of Love alone was he conceived, born, circumciſed, dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:152164:79"/>from his abode, ſubject to <hi>Joſeph,</hi> Baptized, Tempted; out of Love alone he preached, wrought Miracles, broke his Reſt and Sleep: Out of ſingular, tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendent great Love, he left his moſt Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Mother, his Deareſt Friend, his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, ſweat Blood, was in an Agony, was ſeiſed, ſmitten on the Face, endur'd falſe Witneſs, perverſe Judgment, Mockings, Scourgings, condemning to Death, the weight and bitterneſs of the Croſs, and laſt of all the moſt cruel and painful Death: Wherefore to him be Praiſe, Honour and Thankſgiving, now and at all times, even for ever and ever, Amen.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>
                           <date>
                              <hi>An.Dom.</hi> 1518.</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <signed>Jeſus thine I am, ſave me <hi>B.J. von staupitz.</hi>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </text>
            <text xml:lang="eng">
               <front>
                  <div type="title_page">
                     <pb facs="tcp:152164:79"/>
                     <p>The Second TREATISE Concerning the Holy Chriſtian Faith.</p>
                     <p>By Dr. <hi>John Von Staupitz.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="preface">
                     <pb facs="tcp:152164:80"/>
                     <pb n="141" facs="tcp:152164:80"/>
                     <head>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</head>
                     <p>IT is a Lamentable Thing, That Chriſtians, ſince the Death and Paſſion of Chriſt, and the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles Deceaſe, are fallen into ſo great an Ignorance of Chriſt and his true Faith, out of which no Man can be ſaved. And though it be difficult to diſpute about the eſtabliſhed and confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Faith, yet Brotherly Love requires every one to give his Neighbour all the Information, Help and Aſſiſtance he can,
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:152164:81"/>that the Foundation of all Good, and the Root of all Vertue, the only Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of the Elect, viz. The firm Hope and true Faith in Chriſt may not pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh or be loſt: Wherefore I think my ſelf oblig'd and bound in Duty, by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of my Function and Calling, to feed the Hungry with the Word of God, or rather to lead and point them to the ſaid Food; and accordingly truſting in God, I have here undertaken to write ſimply of the Faith in Chriſt. He that can do better, let him ſet about it, all to the Glory of God, and the Edificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Amendment of his Neighbour, Amen.</p>
                  </div>
               </front>
               <body>
                  <div n="1" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="143" facs="tcp:152164:81"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> Of the Obligation and Duty that lies upon us to believe, and of the Beginning of the Chriſtian Faith.</head>
                     <p>THere is no Man, I hope ſo dark and blind in his underſtanding, as not to know, that every one is bound in duty to believe the infallible Truth which is god himſelf, and that God is highly diſhonoured, and the Truth blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemed, when this due Faith is not gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to him. It is an unbecoming thing, for one honeſt man not to believe ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in all reaſonable things; yet foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as there is no expreſs command upon us ſo to do; becauſe the Pſalmiſt tells us, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116.11. That all Men are Lyars, this Earthly Faith is left to a mans free Will and pleaſure, whether he will believe or no; foraſmuch as they are only the Words of meer Men. But Gods Word we muſt and are bound al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways to believe, becauſe it is the Truth it ſelf. All Underſtandings muſt deliver
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:152164:82"/>themſelves Captives to the ſame, and all hearts muſt aſſent to it, be the matters never ſo high above our reach and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings, yet we muſt believe them, becauſe <hi>God</hi> hath ſpoken them, without any further queſtioning, or requiring any further proof, or reaſon of them. This is the Beginning of Faith, without which no Man can pleaſe <hi>God.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="chapter">
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Of the Duty and Neceſſity of Faith in Chriſt.</head>
                     <p>OUr Heavenly Father has revealed much Truth to his Elect, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to them great Grace and many Good things, and thereby in Duty bound them, foraſmuch as he is the Eternal Truth, undoubtedly to believe and look for the ſame at his hands. Whoſoever we are, whether Good or Bad, Jews or Gentiles, the Divine Promiſe neither can nor may be procur'd or haſtened by our Vertues, or hindred by our ſins, but continues eternally unchangeable and conſtant in it's Truth. Wherefore in
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:152164:82"/>order to our receiving the Gifts and Graces of <hi>God</hi> (by whatſoever Names they are called) Faith in Chriſt is abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely neceſſary, whereby we are aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of all the Divine Promiſes. Believe thou therefore, that Jeſus Chriſt is the Son of God; and doubt not in the leaſt, but that in him, through him, and for his ſake all the Good thou enjoyeſt or expecteſt is handed to thee. Believe in him, I ſay, and truſt in him: Is he not the Eſſential Word of God, and the Truth it ſelf? Muſt not he forſake and deny himſelf be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he can forſake or deny thee? And would it not be a plain denying of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, in caſe he ſhould not perform, and make good his Fathers Promiſe to thee? Is it not he that made thee in thy firſt Creation? Is it not he that hath redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thee in the ſecond Birth or Regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? Is it not he that hath wholely and without reſerve, offered up himſelf to his Heavenly Father for thee, and made himſelf one with thee, by feeding thee with his Fleſh and Blood to Eternal Lifes.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="146" facs="tcp:152164:83"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Concerning the Promiſe of the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing in Jeſus Chriſt.</head>
                     <p>GOd promiſed to <hi>Abraham,</hi> that in his Seed all the Nations of the Earth ſhould be bleſſed, and that out of his Seed, even of <hi>Iſaac,</hi> Chriſt ſhould be born; and yet withal God commanded him to ſlay and offer up this his Son <hi>Iſaak Abraham</hi> was obedient to the Divine Command; and, notwithſtanding all Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections, crowding in upon him, firmly believ'd Gods Promiſe, without the leaſt ſtaggering, or being ſollicitous, how the Promiſe could be fulfilled, if he ſhould ſlay his Son <hi>Iſaak</hi> in his youth; but caſt all his care upon God, not doubting, but he would know how to make good his own Word, and perform his Promiſe: O what a gracious Promiſe was this? what a ſtrong and unqueſtionable aſſurance, and what a gracious, paternal Perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance and Accompliſhment? What God then promiſed, he hath ſince made good and performed: for <hi>we have ſeen
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:152164:83"/>his Glory</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>John chap.</hi> 1.14.) <hi>the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry as of the only begotten Son of the Father, full of Grace and Truth.</hi> Who could be more ſure to perform this for us, than he who is Truth it ſelf? And who beſides, is bound to us in ſuch an intimate Tye of the higheſt Love, that he rather choſe to die for us, than that we ſhould fail, or fall ſhort of the leaſt of his Fathers Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes? Wherefore it is impoſſible for thee to believe in Chriſt, but that at the ſame time thou muſt be Bleſſed of God; for Heaven and Earth may paſs away, but the Word of God abides for ever. Alas! What is it that blinds us, poor wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched Creatures? We pretend to believe, That God is become Man, and yet doubt of the performance of the Bleſſing an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>next to it by God himſelf. What grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Affront can we put upon Eternal Truth? Or what greater Ingratitude can we expreſs to the unutterable Love of God? It is not enough therefore for us to believe, that God is become Man; but we muſt alſo believe, that it was done for our Good and Benefit, and that by his Incarnation he has put us in poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of whatſoever has been promis'd to
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:152164:84"/>us. Neither may we deſire or look for our Salvation, Bleſſing, Grace and Mercy from any one, but from him alone, and beſides him, take in no other comfort whatſoever. This is it truly and indeed to believe in Chriſt, which is only youch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafed to Gods bleſſed ones. Herein Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans muſt daily exerciſe themſelves, try themſelves and view themſelves, and in caſe they find themſelves doubtful in any thing, they muſt cry to God for the ſtrengthning and increaſing of their Faith. For theſe two things to believe, and earneſtly to deſire it, are very near of kin to each other. But becauſe we have no ſtrong deſire to believe, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore neither do we pray heartily for it. And thus he who is yet weak in Faith may take comfort from the fervent deſire he hath to believe, which alone will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove him before <hi>God.</hi> In a word, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in Chriſt, or at leaſt deſire firmly to believe in him, and then doubt no further, but that thou art bleſſed by him, and in him.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="149" facs="tcp:152164:84"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> Concerning the Promiſe of our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing enlightened by Chriſt.</head>
                     <p>THe Prophet <hi>Jeremy</hi> declares, that they who believe in Chriſt, ſhall not need any Teacher to inſtruct them, how to believe in God. <hi>They ſhall not teach every Man his Brother,</hi> faith God, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.33, 34. <hi>ſaying, know the Lord, for they ſhall all know me from the leaſt of them unto the greateſt of them, and that I will forgive their Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities, and will remember their Sins no more;</hi> yea, what is more; they ſhall know my Will, and do it; for <hi>I will put my Law in their inward Parts, and write it in their hearts, and I will be their God, and they ſhall be my People.</hi> For they believe in the Light, walk in the Light, and are children of the Light. They have Chriſt the Promiſed Meſſiah, in whom God hath placed his word, and who hath ſpoke un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them whatſoever <hi>God</hi> hath comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded him, <hi>and whoſoever will not hearken unto, but deſpiſe the Words, which he ſhall ſpeak in my Name, I will dequire it at his
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:152164:85"/>hands, Deut.</hi> 18.18, 19. To him we muſt <hi>draw near,</hi> and apply our ſelves, <hi>ſo ſhall not our Faces be aſhamed. Him we muſt follow, ſo ſhall we not walk in darkneſs; but have the Light of Life,</hi> which not only enlighteneth us, but alſo quickens and makes us. alive, excites us to all that is good, inflames us with the Divine Love, and lifting us above, and out of our ſelves draws us into himſelf, ſo that we become, extinguiſht in our ſelves, but flaming and enlightned in him, aad delivered from all Blindneſs and Error. Neither indeed is it poſſible, that the Children of Light, <hi>i. e.</hi> ſuch who walk in the Light, ſhould e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver err or go aſtray. Now this <hi>Light</hi> is found in <hi>Faith, i.e.</hi> in <hi>Chriſt.</hi> Wherefore it follows, that they who do not believe in Chriſt, walk in Darkneſs, and are already judged to Eternal Darkneſs, and Damned; whereas they who believe in Chriſt, are and ſhall be enlightened here and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="151" facs="tcp:152164:85"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Concerning the Aſſurance of our being Eternally Foreſeen and Elected of God.</head>
                     <p>IF any Man ſhould become troubled and ſollicitous about, or doubtful of, his Eternal Election, he may eaſily ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie himſelf from the Information <hi>God</hi> hath given him. Whoſoever Believes in Chriſt, fears no condemnation, and ſhall certainly be ſaved, he is one of the Elect, foreſeen and fore-ordained to Salvation, and hath his Name writ in the Book of Life. But <hi>he who doth not Believe in Chriſt</hi> (as was hinted before in <hi>John</hi> 3.15, 18.) <hi>he is already condemned, becauſe he doth not believe in the Name of the only begotten Son of God. For whoſoever is foreknown the ſame is alſo predeſtinated to a Conformity with the Image of the Son of God, and is called to the Chriſtian Faith, Juſtifyed and Glorifyed,</hi> Rom. 8 29. on the other hand, whoſoever is not found in the Faith of Chriſt, he is not predeſtinated to Salvation. What needs
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:152164:86"/>therefore any further queſtioning about the matter. We have here a clear and plain Information, that if we believe in Chriſt, then we have Chriſt, and toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with him, Salvation, and ſhall never periſh. Theſe are they whom the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath drawn to Chriſt, to the end, that he might ſave them, and none of them might be loſt. But why the Father hath foreſeen or predetermined one, and not another, it doth not become us to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire. For this is ſufficient comfort and ſatisfaction to us, that we know that they all are Predeſtinated, that believe in Chriſt.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="153" facs="tcp:152164:86"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> Concerning the Redemption or De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance from Sin.</head>
                     <p>NO Man can ever be deliver'd from his Sin, ſave only through Faith in Chriſt, who is <hi>the Lamb of God, that takes away the Sins of the World. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon him a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e laid the Sins of us all;</hi> he is the <hi>Scape Goat, who carries the Sins of all the World into the Wilderneſs. Without or beſides him there is no Redeemer, Iſa.</hi> 4.3.11. No Confeſſion, no Repentance, no human Work is of any avail in this Caſe, <hi>We muſt believe in Chriſt, or elſe die in our ſins.</hi> Wherefore it is far more neceſſary for us to exerciſe our ſelves in the Faith, than in a Confeſſional at Directory. The <hi>Faith in Chriſt never fails;</hi> the <hi>Faith in Chriſt purifies the heart,</hi> it <hi>juſtifies us, makes us Children of God, obtains Grace of God,</hi> and <hi>renews the whole Man, Mat.</hi> 11.28, 29, 30. <hi>Come hither all ye that labour, and are heavy laden with Sin,</hi> believe in Chriſt, <hi>ſo ſhall ye be refreſhed, and find reſt to your Souls, Joh.</hi> 7.37, 38. <hi>Doth any ene thirſt after the
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:152164:87"/>Divine Grace, let him come</hi> hither <hi>and drink; for he that believes in Chriſt,</hi> as the Scripture ſaith, <hi>out of his Belly ſhall flow Rivers of Living Water:</hi> Faith is the True River of <hi>Jordan,</hi> in which thoſe who are waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, obtain the purity and innocence of Children. Faith is that Fountain that waſheth and purifies from all unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.1, 2. <hi>Come therefore, and buy it without Money, and without Price,</hi> you need not give any thing for it, <hi>for ye are juſtifyed by Grace alone through the Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which is in Chriſt, whom</hi> alone, <hi>God hath ſet and appointed to be our Saviour and gracious Redeemer, only by the Faith in his pretious Blood-ſhedding, for the manifeſting and declaring of his Righteouſneſs, Rom.</hi> 3.24, 25. and 5.1. <hi>By Faith we are ſaved, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Works of Love.</hi> Whence follows, that nothing is more needful for us, than to exerciſe our ſelves in the Faith.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="155" facs="tcp:152164:87"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> Concerning our being ſet free from Damnable Sins.</head>
                     <p>NOtwithſtanding that thoſe who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in Chriſt do fall into Sin, tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs the Laws of <hi>God, Prov.</hi> 24.16. and, it may be, more frequently than thoſe, who do not believe; yet they who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in Chriſt, have the advantage, that their Sins ſhall not be imputed to them to their Condemnation; God will not, becauſe of them, turn away his loving kindneſs from them, but will viſit their tranſgreſſions with his fatherly Rod, and not take his loving kindneſs quite away from them, For ſo <hi>God</hi> declares and teſtifies to <hi>David,</hi> concerning Chriſt, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 89.30, 31, 32, 33. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.12, 13, 14, 15. <hi>And when thy days be fulfilled, and thou ſhalt ſleep with the Fathers, I will ſet up thy Seed after thee, which ſhall proceed out of thy bowels; and I will eſtabliſh and confirm the Throne of his Kingdom for ever, and will exalt him above all the Kings of the Earth. I will be
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:152164:88"/>his Father, and he ſhall be my Son. If his Children forſake my Law, and walk not in my Judgment; if they break my Statutes and keep not my Commandments, then will I viſit their Tranſgreſſion with the Rod, and their Iniquity with Stripes; nevertheleſs my Loving kindneſs will not I utterly take from them, nor break my Covenant made with them, nor alter the thing that is gone out of my Lips.</hi> I will abide true, whether they abide ſo or no. For <hi>whatſoever is</hi> once <hi>born of God, ſhall never ſin, neither can ever ſin unto Death.</hi> Their ſins are always pardonable, if they repent, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they have been once born of <hi>God,</hi> for that Divine Birth, withholds them from ſinning, not their own Virtue, Reaſon or Strength, and preſence of mind. Foraſmuch then, as no Man is born of <hi>God,</hi> but he that believes in Jeſus Chriſt, it is a conſideration above all meaſure, wonderful and terrible to ſee then ſo little exerciſed in, or acquainted with the Faith that is in Chriſt. It were good and neceſſary therefore that the Miniſters of <hi>Gods</hi> Word ſhould continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, in ſeaſon and out of Seaſon, faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully exhort and preſs people to this
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:152164:88"/>Holy Faith. And indeed tho there were no other Fruit of the true Faith in Chriſt, but this only, yet would all men have ſufficient Reaſon to preſs after and deſire it, as being of ſuch abſolute neceſſity to Salvation.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="chapter">
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> Concerning the Encreaſe of Merit.</head>
                     <p>WE all know that no Man can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve or Merit any thing of <hi>God,</hi> or do any good thing, except that he be planted and engrafted by the Father into Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.1, 2, 3.</note> which cannot be by any other way, than through the Faith that is in Chriſt. <hi>I am the Vine, and my Father is the Husband Man. Every Branch in me, that beareth no Fruit he taketh away; and every Branch that bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Fruit, he purgeth it, that it may bring forth more Fruit. As the Branch cannot
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:152164:89"/>bear Fruit of it ſelf, except it abide in the Vine; no more can ye, except ye abide in me. I am the Vine, ye are the Branches. He that abideth in me, and I in him, the ſame bringeth forth much Fruit, for without, or ſever'd from me, ye can do nothing.</hi> He that abideth not in me; the ſame can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bring forth any good Fruit, nor do any good works, but his works will be caſt into the Fire, and be left there. It is clear and evident, that no man can do any thing that is good except he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in Chriſt, for otherwiſe even all his ſeeming Virtues, are no better than Sins, rejected and condemned to the Fire of Hell. What will then become of the ſeeming Virtues of the Heathens, of the Judgment of right Reaſon, and the counting upon our good meaning, without Faith in Chriſt? Since without Chriſt there is indeed no true Virtue, Reaſon or good meaning. And this Doctrine agrees very well with what Jeſus declared to the Jews, when he bad them <hi>labour or work for that Meat, which endureth to Eternal life.</hi> Whereupon when the Jews asked him;<note place="margin">John 6.27, 28.</note> 
                        <hi>What
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:152164:89"/>ſhall we do, that we may work the Works of God?</hi> Jeſus anſwered them ſaying, <hi>this is the Work of God, that ye believe in him, whom he hath ſent.</hi> Therefore we ought and muſt employ and exerciſe our ſelves in thoſe Works that abide to E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Life, <hi>even ſuch as God himſelf works in us, and that flow forth from the Faith, which is in Chriſt,</hi> for they only endure for ever unto Eternal Life; all the reſt will be loſt, fruitleſs and in vain.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="160" facs="tcp:152164:90"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> Concerning the certain Hearing of our Prayers.</head>
                     <p>IF <hi>ye abide in me,</hi> ſaith our Saviour, <hi>and my words abide in you, ye ſhall ask what ye will, and it ſhall be done unto you.</hi> Joh. 15.7. And again, <hi>Whatſoever ye ſhall ask in my Name, I will do it.</hi> Joh. 14.13, 14. As if he had ſaid, as long as men do not ask in my Name, they have no aſſurance of being heard: But if you do ask in my Name, then need you no other Interceſſor, <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.26, 27. <hi>For the Heavenly Father himſelf loveth you, becauſe ye have loved me, and believed that I came forth from God.</hi> If therefore any one would be ſure, that his Prayers are heard, let him believe in Chriſt: For he that believeth in Chriſt, is beloved of God, and needs no other Inte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>ſſor. But if all the Saints in Heaven ſhould pray for thee, and thou have no Faith in Chriſt, it would be all in vain and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable to thee</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="161" facs="tcp:152164:90"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. X.</hi> Concerning our indiſſoluble Union with Chriſt.</head>
                     <p>THE Faith that is in Chriſt, ſuffers no man to remain or abide in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, but draws us out, and raiſeth us above our ſelves, and never ceaſeth, till it have united us unto God. In the firſt place God doth ſo unite all Believers amongſt themſelves, that they all become one Heart and one Soul in God, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Chriſt's Prayer is heard and fulfilled, which he prayed to the Father for them, <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.11, 19. <hi>Holy Father, keep through thine one Name, thoſe whom thou haſt given me, that they may be one, as we are one.</hi> Which Words do not only reſpect the Twelve Apoſtles of Chriſt, but all thoſe that for the future ſhould believe on him through their Word, as the Text mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly holds forth; and this is the only true Ground and Original of the Unity of the Church. Now all that believe in Chriſt, ſhall in like manner be united
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:152164:91"/>in, and with God, as the Father in Chriſt, and Chriſt in the Father are of one Will, one Mind, one Senſe, one Meaning and one Deſire. Moreover God doth ſo unite all thoſe that believe in Chriſt, with Chriſt, that they become one Body with him, of which he is the Head, and they the Members; and as all the Members are Ruled and Influen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by the Head, ſo are they Govern'd and led by Chriſt, in Chriſt, ſo that no body can be helpful or advantageous to them, as to their inward guidance in the Spirit, ſave the only moſt intimate Jeſus. With reſpect to this intimate Union Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus ſaid; Saul, Saul, <hi>why perſecuteſt thou me?</hi> Act. 9.4. As if he himſelf had been only concern'd, whereas indeed he perſecuted thoſe that believed in him. By means of this Myſtical Union, Chriſt poures forth all Spiritual Gifts and Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces into our heart, through the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> yea and his very ſelf too. But beſides this Union, there is yet another; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by God the Father, Eſpouſeth thoſe to Chriſt that believe in him; ſo that a Believer and Chriſt are inſeperably Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and Joyned together, in the indiſſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:152164:91"/>Band of Wedlock. This Marriage-band, is the Marriage in Paradiſe, a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament and Seal, that Chriſt hath taken upon him all our Weakneſſes, Defects, Wants and Sins, <hi>and is become: Sin for us, that we might become the Righteouſneſs of God in him;</hi> and made <hi>our Wiſdom, Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, Sanctification and Redemption,</hi> not without us, but within us. To us Chriſt is given, to us he is born, and for us he dyed; his Life, Death and Suffering, his Doctrine and Works, are wholely ours, and we in Chriſt, through Faith, are uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and made one with God. This is the Eternal, Heavenly Marriage Band, that we abide eternally betrothed, joyned and united with Chriſt, foraſmuch as we are born of God himſelf, and ſtill-are in him who hath born us. And this is, and is called <hi>Faith, viz.</hi> Chriſt dwelling in us, and that is the true Love, <hi>viz.</hi> God and his Holy Spirit in us. This is the higheſt Union, in the which Chriſt, and he that believes in him, give up themſelves wholely into God, that he alone may be All in All, and work All in All. Of this Union much might be ſaid, but it is above our Underſtanding, and as long as
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:152164:92"/>this Life laſteth, it will but be in part with us. However this is, and abides undoubtedly true, that he who believes in Jeſus Chriſt, becomes thereby Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally united to God: <hi>For he that cleav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to the Lord, becomes one Spirit with him,</hi> which God of his Mercy grant un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>Dr.</hi> John <hi>of</hi> Staupitz.</signed>
                     </closer>
                     <trailer>Jeſu thine I am, Save me.</trailer>
                     <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152164:92"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152164:93"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152164:93" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </text>
         </group>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
